<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>Bitmap</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Display</module>
    <comment>Represents a pixel buffer used for drawing, image transfer and display backing.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>ff557b59</id>
    <idstring>BITMAP</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2003-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The Bitmap class describes a rectangular block of pixel data together with its dimensions, colour format, palette, clipping region and drawing state.  Bitmaps are used directly by <class name="Display">Display</class> and <class name="Picture">Picture</class> objects and provide the low-level pixel storage behind much of Kōtuku's 2D graphics pipeline.</p>
<p>To create a bitmap, set <fl>Width</fl> and <fl>Height</fl> before initialisation.  The pixel format can be selected explicitly with <fl>BitsPerPixel</fl>, <fl>BytesPerPixel</fl>, <fl>AmtColours</fl> and <fl>Type</fl>, or left for <action>Query</action> and <action>Init</action> to derive from the current display environment.  <fl>DataFlags</fl> controls whether the bitmap uses regular CPU-accessible memory or a platform-specific video or texture resource where supported.</p>
<p>Direct CPU access is reliable for regular data bitmaps.  Bitmaps backed by video or texture resources may require <action>Lock</action> before reading or writing <fl>Data</fl>, and <action>Unlock</action> after direct access is complete.  Code that uses the drawing methods exposed by this class does not normally need to manage locking itself.</p>
<p>Bitmap methods are intentionally low-level and operate on immediate pixel data.  Use the Vector module when retained scene graphs, paths, gradients, filters or higher-level drawing composition are required.  Use <class name="Picture">Picture</class> when decoding or encoding image formats is the main concern.</p>
<p>Raw image bytes can be read and written with <action>Read</action> and <action>Write</action>.  <action>SaveImage</action> writes the clipped bitmap image as PCX data to a destination object that supports writing.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file>class_bitmap.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Clear</name>
      <comment>Clears the bitmap image to <fl>BkgdIndex</fl>.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acClear(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acClear()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Clear fills the full bitmap with the current background colour.  The colour used by the operation is <fl>BkgdIndex</fl>, which is derived from <fl>Bkgd</fl> when the background colour is set through the RGB field.</p>
<p>To clear a bitmap to a different colour without changing the background fields, call <method>DrawRectangle</method> with <code>BAF::FILL</code>. For alpha-capable bitmaps, setting <fl>BkgdIndex</fl> to zero is an efficient way to clear the image to transparent black.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="LockFailed">Failed to lock a required resource</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>CopyData</name>
      <comment>Copies bitmap image data to other bitmaps with colour remapping enabled.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acCopyData(*Object, OBJECTID Dest)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acCopyData(Dest:obj)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="OBJECTID" name="Dest">The unique ID of the destination object.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>CopyData copies this bitmap into another initialised <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> object.  Other destination classes are not supported.</p>
<p>The copy is clipped to the destination dimensions.  If the destination is wider or taller than the source, the exposed area is cleared to the destination bitmap's background colour.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Draw</name>
      <comment>Clears the bitmap image to <fl>BkgdIndex</fl>.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDraw(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDraw(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">The X position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">The Y position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">The width of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">The height of the region to be drawn.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Draw fills the full bitmap with the current background colour.  It is equivalent to drawing a filled rectangle over the entire bitmap with <fl>BkgdIndex</fl>.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Flush</name>
      <comment>Flushes pending graphics operations and returns when the accelerator is idle.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acFlush(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acFlush()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Flush synchronises pending graphics operations with the active graphics backend.  Synchronisation is required before direct CPU access to accelerator-managed bitmap memory.</p>
<p>Clients do not need to call this function if solely using the graphics methods provided in the <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> class.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Init</name>
      <comment>Initialises a bitmap.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR InitObject(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.init()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Init prepares a queried bitmap for use.  It validates the calculated bitmap state, allocates <fl>Data</fl> when required, configures platform-specific backing resources and selects the pixel access routines used by drawing operations.</p>
<p>If <fl>Data</fl> has already been supplied, Init uses the caller-provided memory.  Otherwise allocation is controlled by <fl>DataFlags</fl> and <fl>Flags</fl>.  <fl>Width</fl> and <fl>Height</fl> must be set before this action is called.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="Query">Attempt to Query() failed</error>
        <error code="FieldNotSet">A required field value is undefined</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">AllocMemory() failed to create a new memory block</error>
        <error code="SystemCall">A call to the host system has failed</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Lock</name>
      <comment>Locks the bitmap surface for direct read/write access.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acLock(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acLock()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Lock makes bitmap memory available through <fl>Data</fl> for direct CPU access.  It is mainly required for bitmaps backed by a video or platform drawable resource; data-backed bitmaps are already CPU-accessible.</p>
<p>Call <action>Unlock</action> when direct access is complete so platform resources can be released or synchronised.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoData">No data is available for use</error>
        <error code="LockFailed">Failed to lock a required resource</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="FieldNotSet">A required field value is undefined</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">AllocMemory() failed to create a new memory block</error>
        <error code="SystemCall">A call to the host system has failed</error>
        <error code="CreateResource">Failed to create a new resource</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Query</name>
      <comment>Populates a bitmap with pre-initialised/default values prior to initialisation.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acQuery(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acQuery()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Query calculates the bitmap's derived fields without allocating image memory.  It resolves values such as <fl>Type</fl>, <fl>BytesPerPixel</fl>, <fl>BitsPerPixel</fl>, <fl>AmtColours</fl>, <fl>ByteWidth</fl>, <fl>LineWidth</fl>, <fl>PlaneMod</fl> and <fl>Size</fl> from the fields already set by the caller.</p>
<p>At minimum, <fl>Width</fl> and <fl>Height</fl> must be positive.  If format fields are incomplete, Query derives a compatible format where possible; for example, <fl>BytesPerPixel</fl> set to <code>2</code> implies a 16-bit bitmap.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="InvalidDimension">A dimension specification is invalid</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Read</name>
      <comment>Reads raw image data from a bitmap object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acRead(*Object, APTR Buffer, INT Length, INT *Result)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Result:num = Object.acRead(Buffer:str, Length:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="APTR" name="Buffer">Points a buffer that will receive the data.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Length">The total number of bytes to read from the object.  This value cannot exceed the size of the Buffer.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Result">The Read action will write this parameter with the total number of bytes read into the Buffer.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Read copies bytes from <fl>Data</fl> into the supplied output buffer, starting at <fl>Position</fl>.  <fl>Position</fl> is advanced by the number of bytes copied and the result count is returned in the action arguments.</p>
<p>If the requested length would pass the end of the bitmap data, Read truncates the transfer to the remaining byte count.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoData">No data is available for use</error>
        <error code="OutOfRange">A value is outside of the valid range</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Resize</name>
      <comment>Resizes a bitmap object's dimensions.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acResize(*Object, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DOUBLE Depth)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acResize(Width:num, Height:num, Depth:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">The new width of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">The new height of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Depth">The new depth of the object.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Resize changes <fl>Width</fl>, <fl>Height</fl> and, unless <code>BMF::FIXED_DEPTH</code> is set, <fl>BitsPerPixel</fl>.  Existing image content is not preserved.</p>
<p>If <code>BMF::NEVER_SHRINK</code> is set, requested dimensions smaller than the current bitmap are raised to the current size.  If <code>BMF::CLEAR</code> is set, the resized bitmap is cleared to <fl>Bkgd</fl>.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="UndefinedField">A required field value is undefined</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">AllocMemory() failed to create a new memory block</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>SaveImage</name>
      <comment>Saves the bitmap image to a writable object in PCX format.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acSaveImage(*Object, OBJECTID Dest, CLASSID ClassID)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acSaveImage(Dest:obj, ClassID:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="OBJECTID" name="Dest">Refers to an object that will receive the encoded image data.</param>
        <param type="CLASSID" name="ClassID">The Picture class to use for encoding the image data.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>SaveImage writes the current clipping region to <code>Dest</code> as PCX image data.  Paletted bitmaps are written with a palette; true-colour bitmaps are written as three colour planes.  If <fl>ColourSpace</fl> is <code>CS::LINEAR_RGB</code>, RGB values are converted to sRGB while the image is written.</p>
<p>Errors returned by the destination object's Write action are propagated to the caller.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">AllocMemory() failed to create a new memory block</error>
        <error code="BufferOverflow">A buffer overflow has occurred</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Seek</name>
      <comment>Changes the current byte position for read/write operations.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acSeek(*Object, DOUBLE Offset, INT Position)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acSeek(Offset:num, Position:SEEK)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Offset">The desired offset to seek to, relative to the Position parameter.</param>
        <param type="POS" name="Position">The position that defines the starting point for Offset.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Seek sets <fl>Position</fl> from the supplied byte offset and origin.  Positions before the start of the bitmap are clamped to zero, and positions beyond <fl>Size</fl> are clamped to <fl>Size</fl>.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Unlock</name>
      <comment>Unlocks the bitmap surface once direct access is no longer required.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acUnlock(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acUnlock()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Unlock releases or synchronises any platform resources held for direct CPU access after <action>Lock</action>.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Write</name>
      <comment>Writes raw image data to a bitmap object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acWrite(*Object, APTR Buffer, INT Length, INT Result)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Result:num = Object.acWrite(Buffer:str, Length:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="APTR" name="Buffer">A buffer containing the data that will be written to the object.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Length">The total number of bytes to write to the object.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Result">This parameter with be updated with the total number of bytes written from the Buffer.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Write copies bytes from the supplied input buffer into <fl>Data</fl>, starting at <fl>Position</fl>.  <fl>Position</fl> is advanced by the number of bytes written and the result count is returned in the action arguments.</p>
<p>The write must fit within the bitmap's allocated <fl>Size</fl>.  Use <action>Seek</action> to change the target position before writing.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoData">No data is available for use</error>
        <error code="OutOfSpace">Out of space.  There is no available room to complete the request</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <methods>
    <method>
      <name>Compress</name>
      <comment>Compresses bitmap data to save memory.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::Compress(OBJECTPTR Object, INT Level)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Compress(Level:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="Level">Reserved compression level.  The current implementation uses the compression module's default level.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Compress() stores a compressed copy of the bitmap's pixel data and releases the uncompressed <fl>Data</fl> buffer.  It is useful for large data-backed bitmaps that need to remain available but are accessed infrequently.</p>
<p>Once a bitmap is compressed, <fl>Data</fl> is no longer available for direct access.  Call <method>Decompress</method> before reading pixels, writing pixels or passing the bitmap to code that expects an active data buffer.</p>
<p>The <code>BMF::COMPRESSED</code> flag is set in <fl>Flags</fl> after successful compression.  Video and texture-backed bitmaps are not supported by this method.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">AllocMemory() failed to create a new memory block</error>
        <error code="ReallocMemory">The reallocation of a memory block failed</error>
        <error code="CreateObject">A Compression object could not be created.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
        <error code="Compression">Unspecified failure during compression of a data stream</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>ConvertToLinear</name>
      <comment>Converts a bitmap's colour space to linear RGB.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::ConvertToLinear(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = ConvertToLinear()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>ConvertToLinear() converts the bitmap's clipped region from sRGB to linear RGB.  If <code>BMF::ALPHA_CHANNEL</code> is set, pixels with an alpha value of zero are left unchanged.</p>
<p>
<fl>ColourSpace</fl> is set to <code>CS::LINEAR_RGB</code> on completion.  The method returns <code>ERR::NothingDone</code> if the bitmap is already marked as linear RGB.</p>
<p>This method currently requires a 32-bit bitmap.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NothingDone">The Bitmap's content is already in linear RGB format.</error>
        <error code="InvalidDimension">The clipping region is invalid.</error>
        <error code="InvalidState">The Bitmap is not in the expected state.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>ConvertToRGB</name>
      <comment>Converts a bitmap's colour space to standard RGB.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::ConvertToRGB(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = ConvertToRGB()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>ConvertToRGB() converts the bitmap's clipped region from linear RGB to sRGB.  If <code>BMF::ALPHA_CHANNEL</code> is set, pixels with an alpha value of zero are left unchanged.</p>
<p>
<fl>ColourSpace</fl> is set to <code>CS::SRGB</code> on completion.  The method returns <code>ERR::NothingDone</code> if the bitmap is already marked as sRGB.</p>
<p>This method currently requires a 32-bit bitmap.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NothingDone">The bitmap's content is already in sRGB format.</error>
        <error code="InvalidDimension">The clipping region is invalid.</error>
        <error code="InvalidState">The bitmap is not in the expected state.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>CopyArea</name>
      <comment>Copies a rectangular area from one bitmap to another.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::CopyArea(OBJECTPTR Object, objBitmap * DestBitmap, BAF Flags, INT X, INT Y, INT Width, INT Height, INT XDest, INT YDest)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = CopyArea(DestBitmap:obj, Flags:num, X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num, XDest:num, YDest:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="objBitmap *" name="DestBitmap">The target bitmap.</param>
        <param type="BAF" name="Flags" lookup="BAF">Optional flags.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="X">The horizontal position of the area to be copied.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">The vertical position of the area to be copied.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">The width of the area.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">The height of the area.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="XDest">The horizontal position to copy the area to.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="YDest">The vertical position to copy the area to.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>CopyArea() copies a rectangular region from this bitmap to <code>DestBitmap</code>.  The source rectangle starts at <code>X</code>, <code>Y</code> and has the supplied <code>Width</code> and <code>Height</code>; the destination position is <code>XDest</code>, <code>YDest</code>.</p>
<p>The operation is implemented by <function module="Display">CopyArea</function> and supports the same <lk>BAF</lk> options.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Mismatch">The target bitmap is not a close enough match to the source bitmap in order to perform the operation.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>Decompress</name>
      <comment>Decompresses a compressed bitmap.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::Decompress(OBJECTPTR Object, INT RetainData)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Decompress(RetainData:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="RetainData">Retains the compression data if <code>true</code>.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Decompress() restores <fl>Data</fl> for a bitmap previously compressed with <method>Compress</method>.  If no compressed data is available, the method returns <code>ERR::Okay</code> without changing the bitmap.</p>
<p>Compressed data is released after a successful restore unless <code>RetainData</code> is <code>true</code>.  Retaining it allows the most recent compressed image to be restored again later.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">Insufficient memory in recreating the bitmap data buffer.</error>
        <error code="CreateObject">A Compression object could not be created.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>Demultiply</name>
      <comment>Reverses the conversion process performed by Premultiply().</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::Demultiply(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Demultiply()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Demultiply() restores straight RGB channel values after <method>Premultiply</method> has converted them to premultiplied alpha.  The method returns <code>ERR::NothingDone</code> if <code>BMF::PREMUL</code> is not set in <fl>Flags</fl>.</p>
<p>This method operates only on 32-bit bitmaps that have an alpha channel, and it processes only the current clipping region.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NothingDone">The content is already normalised.</error>
        <error code="InvalidDimension">The clipping region is invalid.</error>
        <error code="InvalidState">The Bitmap is not in the expected state (32-bit with an alpha channel).</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>DrawRectangle</name>
      <comment>Draws rectangles, both filled and unfilled.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::DrawRectangle(OBJECTPTR Object, INT X, INT Y, INT Width, INT Height, UINT Colour, BAF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = DrawRectangle(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num, Colour:num, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">The left-most coordinate of the rectangle.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">The top-most coordinate of the rectangle.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">The width of the rectangle.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">The height of the rectangle.</param>
        <param type="UINT" name="Colour">The colour index to use for the rectangle.</param>
        <param type="BAF" name="Flags" lookup="BAF">Supports <code>FILL</code> and <code>BLEND</code>.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>This method draws both filled and unfilled rectangles.  The rectangle is drawn to the target bitmap at position <code>(X, Y)</code> with dimensions determined by the specified <code>Width</code> and <code>Height</code>.  If the <code>Flags</code> parameter sets the <code>FILL</code> flag then the rectangle will be filled, otherwise the rectangle's outline will be drawn.  The colour of the rectangle is determined by the pixel value in the <code>Colour</code> parameter.</p>
<p>The draw operation is clipped to the bitmap's current clipping region.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>GetColour</name>
      <comment>Converts Red, Green, Blue components into a single colour value.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::GetColour(OBJECTPTR Object, INT Red, INT Green, INT Blue, INT Alpha, UINT * Colour)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Colour:num = GetColour(Red:num, Green:num, Blue:num, Alpha:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="Red">Red component from 0 - 255.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Green">Green component from 0 - 255.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Blue">Blue component value from 0 - 255.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Alpha">Alpha component value from 0 - 255.</param>
        <param type="UINT *" name="Colour">The resulting colour value will be returned here.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>The GetColour() method is used to convert <code>Red</code>, <code>Green</code>, <code>Blue</code> and <code>Alpha</code> colour components into a single colour index that can be used for directly writing colours to the bitmap.  The result is returned in the <code>Colour</code> parameter.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>Premultiply</name>
      <comment>Premultiplies RGB channel values by the alpha channel.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::Premultiply(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Premultiply()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Premultiply() converts RGB values in the current clipping region to premultiplied-alpha form.  The formula applied to each colour channel is <code>(Colour * Alpha + 0xff)&gt;&gt;8</code>.  The alpha channel is not changed.</p>
<p>This method operates only on 32-bit bitmaps that have an alpha channel.  If the bitmap is already marked as premultiplied, the method returns <code>ERR::NothingDone</code>.</p>
<p>The process can be reversed with a call to <method>Demultiply</method>.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NothingDone">The content is already premultiplied.</error>
        <error code="InvalidDimension">The clipping region is invalid.</error>
        <error code="InvalidState">The Bitmap is not in the expected state (32-bit with an alpha channel)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SetClipRegion</name>
      <comment>Sets a clipping region for a bitmap object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR bmp::SetClipRegion(OBJECTPTR Object, INT Number, INT Left, INT Top, INT Right, INT Bottom, INT Terminate)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SetClipRegion(Number:num, Left:num, Top:num, Right:num, Bottom:num, Terminate:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="Number">The number of the clip region to set.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Left">The horizontal start of the clip region.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Top">The vertical start of the clip region.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Right">The exclusive right edge of the clip region.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Bottom">The exclusive bottom edge of the clip region.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Terminate">Set to <code>true</code> if this is the last clip region in the list, otherwise <code>false</code>.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>SetClipRegion() updates one entry in the bitmap's clipping region list.  Drawing operations are restricted to the combined region.</p>
<p>This method is implemented by <function module="Display">SetClipRegion</function>.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

  </methods>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>AmtColours</name>
      <comment>The maximum number of colours represented by the bitmap format.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>For indexed bitmaps, this is the size of the usable palette.  For direct-colour bitmaps, it reflects the colour range implied by <fl>BitsPerPixel</fl> and the selected <fl>ColourFormat</fl>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BitsPerPixel</name>
      <comment>The number of bits used to represent each pixel.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This includes all bits used by the pixel format, including alpha bits where present.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Bkgd</name>
      <comment>Background colour in RGB format.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>RGB8</type>
      <description>
<p>The background colour is used by operations that need a default fill colour, such as <action>Clear</action>, <action>Draw</action> and some resize paths.  The default background colour is black.</p>
<p>The <fl>BkgdIndex</fl> will be updated as a result of setting this field.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BkgdIndex</name>
      <comment>Background colour as a packed pixel value or palette index.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Use <fl>Bkgd</fl> for most updates.  Set BkgdIndex directly only when the caller has already calculated the target bitmap's native pixel value or palette index.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BlendMode</name>
      <comment>Defines the blending algorithm to use when rendering transparent pixels.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type lookup="BLM">BLM</type>
      <description>
<p>The default value is <code>BLM::AUTO</code>, which selects the preferred blending path for the current bitmap and graphics backend.</p>
<types lookup="BLM"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ByteWidth</name>
      <comment>The width of the bitmap, in bytes.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>ByteWidth is calculated from <fl>Width</fl>, <fl>Type</fl> and <fl>BytesPerPixel</fl>.  It describes the meaningful pixel bytes in a row and does not include alignment padding.</p>
<p>The formulas used to calculate the value of this field are:</p>
<pre>Planar      = Width/8
Chunky/8    = Width
Chunky/15   = Width * 2
Chunky/16   = Width * 2
Chunky/24   = Width * 3
Chunky/32   = Width * 4
</pre>
<p>To learn the total byte-width per line including any additional padded bytes, refer to the <fl>LineWidth</fl> field.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BytesPerPixel</name>
      <comment>The number of bytes per pixel.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field reflects the byte count used by one chunky pixel.  Values normally range from 1 to 4.  For planar bitmaps, <fl>BitsPerPixel</fl> is the more useful format indicator.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Clip</name>
      <comment>Defines the bitmap's clipping region.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>struct ClipRectangle</type>
      <description>
<p>Clip is a shorthand reference for <fl>ClipLeft</fl>, <fl>ClipTop</fl>, <fl>ClipRight</fl> and <fl>ClipBottom</fl>, returning all four values as a single <st>ClipRectangle</st> structure.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ClipBottom</name>
      <comment>The exclusive bottom edge of the bitmap clipping region.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The default clipping region matches the bitmap dimensions.  Drawing operations are limited to the active clipping region.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ClipLeft</name>
      <comment>The left-most edge of a bitmap's clipping region.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The default clipping region matches the bitmap dimensions.  Drawing operations are limited to the active clipping region.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ClipRight</name>
      <comment>The exclusive right edge of the bitmap clipping region.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The default clipping region matches the bitmap dimensions.  Drawing operations are limited to the active clipping region.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ClipTop</name>
      <comment>The top-most edge of a bitmap's clipping region.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The default clipping region matches the bitmap dimensions.  Drawing operations are limited to the active clipping region.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ColourFormat</name>
      <comment>Describes the colour format used to construct each bitmap pixel.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>struct ColourFormat *</type>
      <description>
<p>ColourFormat points to the structure that describes how packed pixel values map to red, green, blue and alpha channels. It is relevant for direct-colour bitmaps, normally those with two or more bytes per pixel.</p>
<struct lookup="ColourFormat"/>
<p>The following C++ helper methods can be called on a bitmap to build packed colour values from channel components:</p>
<pre>packPixel(Red, Green, Blue)
packPixel(Red, Green, Blue, Alpha)
packAlpha(Alpha)
packPixelRGB(RGB8 &amp;RGB)
packPixelRGBA(RGB8 &amp;RGB)
</pre>
<p>The following C macros are optimised forms for 24 and 32-bit bitmaps:</p>
<pre>PackPixelWB(Red, Green, Blue)
PackPixelWBA(Red, Green, Blue, Alpha)
</pre>
<p>The following C++ helper methods unpack individual colour components from a packed colour value:</p>
<pre>unpackRed(Colour)
unpackGreen(Colour)
unpackBlue(Colour)
unpackAlpha(Colour)
</pre>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ColourSpace</name>
      <comment>Defines the colour space for RGB values.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type lookup="CS">CS</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="CS"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Data</name>
      <comment>Pointer to a bitmap's data area.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UINT8 *</type>
      <description>
<p>Data points to the first byte of the bitmap's pixel buffer when CPU-visible memory is available.  Caller-supplied memory can be used for data-backed bitmaps, but most callers should let <action>Init</action> allocate the correctly sized buffer.</p>
<p>For video or texture-backed bitmaps, <fl>Data</fl> may be unavailable until <action>Lock</action> succeeds.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DataFlags</name>
      <comment>Defines the memory flags to use in allocating a bitmap's data area.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="MEM">MEM</type>
      <description>
<p>DataFlags controls the kind of backing storage requested during initialisation.  Common values are <code>MEM::DATA</code>, <code>MEM::VIDEO</code> and <code>MEM::TEXTURE</code>.</p>
<p>Video or texture-backed bitmaps can be faster for some drawing paths, but direct CPU access is platform dependent.  Use <action>Lock</action> before reading or writing <fl>Data</fl> directly when the bitmap is not a regular data bitmap.</p>
<types lookup="MEM"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DrawUCPixel</name>
      <comment>Points to a C function that draws pixels to the bitmap using colour indexes.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type prototype="void (*DrawUCPixel)(objBitmap *, int, int, uint32_t)">FUNCTION *</type>
      <description>
<p>DrawUCPixel points to the active low-level pixel writer for packed colour or palette-index values.  It is intended for C callers that need direct pixel access.  No clipping or bounds checks are performed.</p>
<p>The prototype of the DrawUCPixel function is <code>Function(*Bitmap, LONG X, LONG Y, uint32_t Colour)</code>.</p>
<p>The new pixel value is supplied in the <code>Colour</code> parameter.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DrawUCRIndex</name>
      <comment>Points to a C function that draws pixels to the bitmap in RGB format.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type prototype="void (*DrawUCRIndex)(objBitmap *, uint8_t *, struct RGB8 *)">FUNCTION *</type>
      <description>
<p>DrawUCRIndex points to the active low-level RGB pixel writer for a caller-supplied address inside <fl>Data</fl>.  It is intended for C callers that need direct pixel access.  No clipping, bounds or address validation is performed.</p>
<p>The prototype of the DrawUCRIndex function is <code>Function(*Bitmap, uint8_t *Data, RGB8 *RGB)</code>.</p>
<p>The Data parameter must point to a location within the Bitmap's graphical address space.  The new pixel value must be defined in the <code>RGB</code> parameter.</p>
<p>There is no colour-index equivalent because callers can write indexed pixel bytes directly through <fl>Data</fl>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DrawUCRPixel</name>
      <comment>Points to a C function that draws pixels to the bitmap in RGB format.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type prototype="void (*DrawUCRPixel)(objBitmap *, int, int, struct RGB8 *)">FUNCTION *</type>
      <description>
<p>DrawUCRPixel points to the active low-level RGB pixel writer for <code>X</code>, <code>Y</code> coordinates.  It is intended for C callers that need direct pixel access.  No clipping or bounds checks are performed.</p>
<p>The prototype of the DrawUCRPixel function is <code>Function(*Bitmap, LONG X, LONG Y, RGB8 *RGB)</code>.</p>
<p>The new pixel value must be defined in the <code>RGB</code> parameter.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Flags</name>
      <comment>Optional flags.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="BMF">BMF</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="BMF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Height</name>
      <comment>The height of the bitmap, in pixels.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>LineWidth</name>
      <comment>The length of each bitmap line in bytes, including alignment.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>LineWidth includes any row padding required by the active bitmap type or platform backend.  Use <fl>ByteWidth</fl> for the number of meaningful pixel bytes in a row.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Opacity</name>
      <comment>Determines the translucency setting to use in drawing operations.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Opacity is an 8-bit alpha multiplier used by drawing operations that support translucent bitmap copies.  A value of <code>255</code> is fully opaque and disables additional translucency.  Lower values make copied pixels more transparent.</p>
<p>This value is separate from any per-pixel alpha channel stored in the bitmap.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Palette</name>
      <comment>Points to a bitmap's colour palette.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>struct RGBPalette *</type>
      <description>
<p>Palette points to the bitmap's colour table.  Indexed bitmaps use this table to map pixel values to RGB colours, and some conversion paths use it even when the bitmap itself is direct-colour.</p>
<p>The structure starts with the palette header and colour count, followed by colour entries in index order.  There is no terminating entry.</p>
<p>The following example is for a 32 colour palette:</p>
<pre>RGBPalette Palette = {
  ID_PALETTE, VER_PALETTE, 32,
  {{ 0x00,0x00,0x00 }, { 0x10,0x10,0x10 }, { 0x17,0x17,0x17 }, { 0x20,0x20,0x20 },
   { 0x27,0x27,0x27 }, { 0x30,0x30,0x30 }, { 0x37,0x37,0x37 }, { 0x40,0x40,0x40 },
   { 0x47,0x47,0x47 }, { 0x50,0x50,0x50 }, { 0x57,0x57,0x57 }, { 0x60,0x60,0x60 },
   { 0x67,0x67,0x67 }, { 0x70,0x70,0x70 }, { 0x77,0x77,0x77 }, { 0x80,0x80,0x80 },
   { 0x87,0x87,0x87 }, { 0x90,0x90,0x90 }, { 0x97,0x97,0x97 }, { 0xa0,0xa0,0xa0 },
   { 0xa7,0xa7,0xa7 }, { 0xb0,0xb0,0xb0 }, { 0xb7,0xb7,0xb7 }, { 0xc0,0xc0,0xc0 },
   { 0xc7,0xc7,0xc7 }, { 0xd0,0xd0,0xd0 }, { 0xd7,0xd7,0xd7 }, { 0xe0,0xe0,0xe0 },
   { 0xe0,0xe0,0xe0 }, { 0xf0,0xf0,0xf0 }, { 0xf7,0xf7,0xf7 }, { 0xff,0xff,0xff }
   }
};
</pre>
<p>Palettes are created for all bitmap types, including RGB bitmaps above 8-bit colour, because several drawing functions use a palette table when converting between bitmap formats.</p>
<p>Parent objects such as <class name="Display">Display</class> may need to be updated separately before palette changes are reflected by the visible display.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>PlaneMod</name>
      <comment>The differential between each bitmap plane.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>PlaneMod specifies the byte distance between each bitplane in planar bitmaps.  For chunky bitmaps, it reflects the total size of the bitmap buffer.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Position</name>
      <comment>The current read/write data position.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Position is the byte offset used by <action>Read</action> and <action>Write</action>.  Use <action>Seek</action> to change it.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ReadUCPixel</name>
      <comment>Points to a C function that reads pixels from the bitmap in colour index format.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type prototype="uint32_t (*ReadUCPixel)(objBitmap *, int, int)">FUNCTION *</type>
      <description>
<p>ReadUCPixel points to the active low-level pixel reader for packed colour or palette-index values.  It is intended for C callers that need direct pixel access.  No clipping or bounds checks are performed.</p>
<p>The prototype of the ReadUCPixel function is <code>Function(*Bitmap, LONG X, LONG Y, LONG *Index)</code>.</p>
<p>The pixel value will be returned in the <code>Index</code> parameter.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ReadUCRIndex</name>
      <comment>Points to a C function that reads pixels from the bitmap in RGB format.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type prototype="void (*ReadUCRIndex)(objBitmap *, uint8_t *, struct RGB8 *)">FUNCTION *</type>
      <description>
<p>ReadUCRIndex points to the active low-level RGB pixel reader for a caller-supplied address inside <fl>Data</fl>.  It is intended for C callers that need direct pixel access.  No clipping, bounds or address validation is performed.</p>
<p>The prototype of the ReadUCRIndex function is <code>Function(*Bitmap, uint8_t *Data, RGB8 *RGB)</code>.</p>
<p>The <code>Data</code> parameter must point to a location within the Bitmap's graphical address space.  The pixel value will be returned in the <code>RGB</code> parameter.</p>
<p>There is no colour-index equivalent because callers can read indexed pixel bytes directly through <fl>Data</fl>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ReadUCRPixel</name>
      <comment>Points to a C function that reads pixels from the bitmap in RGB format.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type prototype="void (*ReadUCRPixel)(objBitmap *, int, int, struct RGB8 *)">FUNCTION *</type>
      <description>
<p>ReadUCRPixel points to the active low-level RGB pixel reader for <code>X</code>, <code>Y</code> coordinates.  It is intended for C callers that need direct pixel access.  No clipping or bounds checks are performed.</p>
<p>The prototype of the ReadUCRPixel function is <code>Function(*Bitmap, LONG X, LONG Y, RGB8 *RGB)</code>.</p>
<p>The pixel value is returned in the <code>RGB</code> parameter.  Because this function expands the pixel value to RGB components, <fl>ReadUCPixel</fl> or <fl>ReadUCRIndex</fl> may be faster when RGB decomposition is not required.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Size</name>
      <comment>The total size of the bitmap, in bytes.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>TransColour</name>
      <comment>The transparent colour of the bitmap, in RGB format.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>RGB8</type>
      <description>
<p>Pixels matching this colour are skipped by drawing operations that honour colour-key transparency.</p>
<p>Do not use colour-key transparency on bitmaps that use alpha transparency.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>TransIndex</name>
      <comment>The transparent colour of the bitmap, represented as an index.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>TransIndex stores the transparent colour as a packed pixel value or palette index.  Pixels matching this value are skipped by drawing operations that honour colour-key transparency.</p>
<p>Use <fl>TransColour</fl> for most updates.  Set TransIndex directly only when the caller has already calculated the target bitmap's native pixel value or palette index.  Do not use colour-key transparency on bitmaps that use alpha transparency.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Type</name>
      <comment>Defines the data type of the bitmap.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="BMP">BMP</type>
      <description>
<p>Type defines the bitmap layout, either <code>BMP::PLANAR</code> for planar bitmaps or <code>BMP::CHUNKY</code> for interleaved pixel data. Chunky is the default.</p>
<types lookup="BMP"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Width</name>
      <comment>The width of the bitmap, in pixels.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Width must be set before <action>Query</action> or <action>Init</action> can derive the bitmap layout.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="BAF" comment="Instructions for basic graphics operations.">
      <const name="BLEND">Enable alpha blending to the destination if the source supports an alpha channel.</const>
      <const name="COPY">Special <function module="Display">CopyArea</function> option that avoids blending when the destination pixel is empty.</const>
      <const name="DITHER">Perform dithering if the colour formats differ between the source and destination.</const>
      <const name="FILL">For primitive operations such as <function module="Display">DrawRectangle</function>, this will fill the shape with a solid colour or texture.</const>
      <const name="LINEAR">Use linear interpolation to improve the quality of alpha blending.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="BLM" comment="Defines the blending algorithm to use when transparent pixels are rendered to the bitmap.">
      <const name="AUTO">Use the most suitable of the available algorithms.</const>
      <const name="GAMMA">Use gamma correct blending.  This algorithm is slow but produces a high quality result.</const>
      <const name="LINEAR">Use linear blending.  Applicable if the bitmap is in linear colour space.</const>
      <const name="NONE">Never blend transparent pixels, just copy as-is.</const>
      <const name="SRGB">Use sRGB linear blending.  This algorithm is extremely efficient but produces poor quality results.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="BMF" comment="Bitmap flags">
      <const name="ACCELERATED_2D">2D video acceleration is available.</const>
      <const name="ACCELERATED_3D">3D video acceleration is available.</const>
      <const name="ALPHA_CHANNEL">For 32-bit images, indicates that an alpha channel is present.</const>
      <const name="BLANK_PALETTE">Forces a blank/black palette on initialisation.</const>
      <const name="CLEAR">Clear graphics on initialisation and when resizing.</const>
      <const name="COMPRESSED">The bitmap data is compressed.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_DEPTH">Prevent changing of bitmap depth after initialisation (e.g. via <code>Resize()</code>).</const>
      <const name="INVERSE_ALPHA">Indicates reverse alpha blending, higher values are transparent.</const>
      <const name="MASK">Declare the <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> as a 1 or 8 bit mask.  Must be set in conjunction with the <class name="Bitmap" field="BitsPerPixel">Bitmap.BitsPerPixel</class> field on initialisation.</const>
      <const name="NEVER_SHRINK">Ignore resize requests that would shrink the size of the bitmap.</const>
      <const name="NO_DATA">Do not allocate memory in the Data field on initialisation.</const>
      <const name="PREMUL">The RGB values are premultiplied (32-bit only).</const>
      <const name="QUERIED">Automatically set after a <code>Query()</code> on the bitmap.</const>
      <const name="TRANSPARENT">Indicates that the bitmap utilises a transparent colour.  This is automatically set if the <class name="Bitmap" field="TransIndex">Bitmap.TransIndex</class> or <class name="Bitmap" field="TransColour">Bitmap.TransColour</class> is defined, and support exists in functions such as <function module="Display">CopyArea</function>.</const>
      <const name="USER">This user flag can be used to tag bitmaps with special meaning.  Not used internally.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="BMP" comment="Bitmap types">
      <const name="CHUNKY">Chunky pixel mode (default).</const>
      <const name="PLANAR">Planar pixel mode separates pixel bits across multiple planes.  Commonly used for single bit bitmap masks.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="CS" comment="Colour space options.">
      <const name="CIE_LAB">Cartesian L*a*b* colour space defined by CIE 15.</const>
      <const name="CIE_LCH">Polar L*CHab colour space defined by CIE 15.</const>
      <const name="LINEAR_RGB">Linear RGB is used to improve colour balance in blending operations.</const>
      <const name="SRGB">The default colour-space is sRGB.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
    <struct name="ColourFormat" typeName="COLOURFORMAT">
      <field name="RedShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for red (15/16 bit formats only)</field>
      <field name="GreenShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for green</field>
      <field name="BlueShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for blue</field>
      <field name="AlphaShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for alpha</field>
      <field name="RedMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for red (ranges from 0x00 to 0xff)</field>
      <field name="GreenMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for green</field>
      <field name="BlueMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for blue</field>
      <field name="AlphaMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for alpha</field>
      <field name="RedPos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for red</field>
      <field name="GreenPos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for green</field>
      <field name="BluePos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for blue</field>
      <field name="AlphaPos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for alpha</field>
      <field name="BitsPerPixel" type="UINT8">Number of bits per pixel for this format.</field>
    </struct>

  </structs>
</book>
