<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>Clipboard</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Display</module>
    <comment>Manages copied, cut and dragged data for paste operations.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>b5bbe3e7</id>
    <idstring>CLIPBOARD</idstring>
    <category>IO</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2003-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The Clipboard class stores references to copied data so that applications can offer cut, copy, paste and drag-and-drop workflows.  Clipboard entries are grouped by datatype and are exposed to consumers as readable files, allowing large items to be pasted without first loading their contents into application memory.</p>
<p>Multiple Clipboard objects can be created, but they share the same clipboard store for the current process and user session.  Each datatype normally has one active group of items.  Adding a new group for the same datatype replaces the previous group unless the <code>CEF::EXTEND</code> flag is used.</p>
<p>On Windows, text and file references are integrated with the host clipboard when possible, so Kōtuku applications can exchange those datatypes with native Windows applications.  If <code>CPF::HISTORY_BUFFER</code> is enabled, the clipboard actively monitors host changes and caches copied data in the local <code>clipboard:</code> volume.  This enables limited history at the cost of additional monitoring and storage overhead.</p>
<p>On Linux and other non-Windows builds, clipboard storage is local to Kōtuku applications unless platform-specific host integration is supplied by the display driver.</p>
<p>When history buffering is active, a fixed number of clip groups is retained and the oldest group is removed when the limit is exceeded.  Cached clipboard files are kept under <code>clipboard:</code> and stale generated files are cleaned up during display initialisation.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file>class_clipboard.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Clear</name>
      <comment>Removes all cached clipboard data.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acClear(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acClear()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Clear deletes the generated clipboard cache and removes all clip records tracked by the current process.  Use <method>Remove</method> to delete only selected datatypes.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>DataFeed</name>
      <comment>Sends data to the clipboard or handles drag-and-drop requests.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDataFeed(*Object, OBJECTID Object, DATA Datatype, APTR Buffer, INT Size)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDataFeed(Object:obj, Datatype:DATA, Buffer:str)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="OBJECTID" name="Object">Must refer to the unique ID of the object that you represent. If you do not represent an object, set this parameter to the current task ID.</param>
        <param type="DATA" name="Datatype" lookup="DATA">The type of data being sent.</param>
        <param type="APTR" name="Buffer">The data being sent to the target object.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Size">The size of the data in Buffer.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>For regular clipboard writes, DataFeed currently accepts <code>DATA::TEXT</code>.  Text received through this action replaces the current text clip and is cached as a generated file unless the host clipboard accepts it and no history buffer is active.</p>
<p>When the clipboard is in drag-and-drop mode, DataFeed also accepts <code>DATA::REQUEST</code>.  Requests are forwarded to the <fl>RequestHandler</fl> callback so the source application can provide the requested data to the requester.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Terminate">Termination requested</error>
        <error code="Write">Error writing data</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="FieldNotSet">A required field value is undefined</error>
        <error code="CreateObject">A call to CreateObject() failed</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <methods>
    <method>
      <name>AddFile</name>
      <comment>Adds a file reference to the clipboard.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR clip::AddFile(OBJECTPTR Object, CLIPTYPE Datatype, CSTRING Path, CEF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = AddFile(Datatype:num, Path:str, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="CLIPTYPE" name="Datatype" lookup="CLIPTYPE">Identifies the type of data represented by the file.</param>
        <param type="CSTRING" name="Path">Path of the file to add.</param>
        <param type="CEF" name="Flags" lookup="CEF">Optional flags.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Use AddFile() when the data to copy is already available as a file.  The method stores the file path as a clipboard entry and associates it with a <code>CLIPTYPE</code> value so that paste targets can decide whether they understand the content. This is efficient for large items because the clipboard does not need to load the file contents into memory.</p>
<p>If the clipboard can publish the file reference to the host platform, and history buffering is disabled, the method may return after updating the host clipboard.  Otherwise the file reference is recorded in the Kōtuku clipboard store.</p>
<p>Recognised data types are:</p>
<types lookup="CLIPTYPE"/>
<p>Optional flags that may be passed to this method are as follows:</p>
<types lookup="CEF"/>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">The files were added to the clipboard.</error>
        <error code="MissingPath"><code>Path</code> was not specified.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>AddObjects</name>
      <comment>Saves objects to clipboard cache files.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR clip::AddObjects(OBJECTPTR Object, CLIPTYPE Datatype, OBJECTID * Objects, CEF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = AddObjects(Datatype:num, Objects:any, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="CLIPTYPE" name="Datatype" lookup="CLIPTYPE">Type of data represented by the objects, or zero for automatic recognition.</param>
        <param type="OBJECTID *" name="Objects">Zero-terminated array of object IDs to add to the clipboard.</param>
        <param type="CEF" name="Flags" lookup="CEF">Optional flags.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Use AddObjects() to copy one or more objects by asking each object to save itself to a generated file in the <code>clipboard:</code> volume.  This avoids requiring the caller to create temporary files before copying object data.</p>
<p>If <code>Datatype</code> is <code>CLIPTYPE::NIL</code>, the clipboard chooses a datatype from the source object's class where possible. <class name="Picture">Picture</class> objects are stored as <code>CLIPTYPE::IMAGE</code>, sound objects are stored as <code>CLIPTYPE::AUDIO</code>, and unrecognised classes are stored as <code>CLIPTYPE::OBJECT</code>.  Set <code>Datatype</code> explicitly to override this automatic selection.</p>
<p>All objects in a single call must belong to the same class.  The <code>Objects</code> array must be terminated with a zero entry.</p>
<p>Optional flags that may be passed to this method are the same as those specified in the <method>AddFile</method> method.  The <code>CEF::DELETE</code> flag has no effect on objects.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">The objects were added to the clipboard.</error>
        <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
        <error code="Lock">Failed to lock a required resource</error>
        <error code="CreateFile">A new file could not be created</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>AddText</name>
      <comment>Adds a block of text to the clipboard.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR clip::AddText(OBJECTPTR Object, CSTRING String)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = AddText(String:str)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="CSTRING" name="String">UTF-8 text to add to the clipboard.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Use AddText() to place plain UTF-8 text on the clipboard.  Empty strings are ignored and return <code>ERR::Okay</code>.</p>
<p>On Windows, the text is also published to the host clipboard when supported.  If history buffering is disabled and the host clipboard accepts the text, no local cache file is created.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="CreateFile">A new file could not be created</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>GetFiles</name>
      <comment>Retrieve the most recently clipped data as a list of files.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR clip::GetFiles(OBJECTPTR Object, CLIPTYPE Filter, INT Index, CLIPTYPE * Datatype, CSTRING ** Files, CEF * Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Datatype:num, Files:array, Flags:num = GetFiles(Filter:num, Index:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="CLIPTYPE" name="Filter" lookup="CLIPTYPE">Datatype filter.  Set to zero to accept any datatype.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Index">History index to read when Filter is zero.  Zero is the most recent clip group.</param>
        <param type="CLIPTYPE *" name="Datatype" lookup="CLIPTYPE">Datatype of the returned clip group.</param>
        <param type="CSTRING **" name="Files"><code>NULL</code>-terminated list of returned clip file paths.  Release the array with <function module="Core">FreeResource</function>.</param>
        <param type="CEF *" name="Flags" lookup="CEF">Result flags.  If the delete flag is set, delete the files after use to complete a cut operation.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>GetFiles() returns clipboard entries as a <code>NULL</code>-terminated list of readable file paths.  The caller can request a specific set of datatypes through <code>Filter</code>, or pass <code>CLIPTYPE::NIL</code> to accept any datatype.</p>
<p>Without history buffering, only the most recent clip group is available.  With history buffering enabled, pass <code>CLIPTYPE::NIL</code> as <code>Filter</code> and increment <code>Index</code> to scan retained history from newest to oldest until <code>ERR::OutOfRange</code> is returned.</p>
<p>On success, <code>Datatype</code> reports the datatype of the returned clip and <code>Files</code> receives the generated file list.  How the caller reads each file depends on <code>Datatype</code>; <function module="Core">IdentifyFile</function> can also be used to find a class that supports the data.  The returned <code>Files</code> array is allocated for the caller and must be released with <function module="Core">FreeResource</function>.</p>
<p>If <code>CEF::DELETE</code> is returned in <code>Flags</code>, the caller must delete the source files after successfully copying the data in order to complete a cut operation.  When cutting and pasting files within the same file system, <function module="Core">MoveFile</function> is usually the most efficient way to consume those entries.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">A matching clip was found and returned.</error>
        <error code="NoData">No clip was available that matched the requested data type.</error>
        <error code="OutOfRange">The specified <code>Index</code> is out of the range of the available clip items.</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">AllocMemory() failed to create a new memory block</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
      <tags>caller-owns-result</tags>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>Remove</name>
      <comment>Removes selected datatypes from the clipboard.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR clip::Remove(OBJECTPTR Object, CLIPTYPE Datatype)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Remove(Datatype:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="CLIPTYPE" name="Datatype" lookup="CLIPTYPE">Datatype flags to remove.  Values may be combined.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Remove() clears all active clip groups whose datatype matches <code>Datatype</code>.  Multiple datatypes can be removed by combining <code>CLIPTYPE</code> flags.  To clear all content from the clipboard, use <action>Clear</action>.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

  </methods>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Flags</name>
      <comment>Optional clipboard behaviour flags.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="CPF">CPF</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="CPF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>RequestHandler</name>
      <comment>Callback for drag-and-drop data requests.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>FUNCTION</type>
      <description>
<p>When the clipboard is in drag-and-drop mode, applications can request source data by sending a <code>DATA::REQUEST</code> to <action>DataFeed</action>.  The request is forwarded to the callback stored in RequestHandler, which must be supplied by the source application.</p>
<p>The callback uses this signature:</p>
<p>
<code>ERR RequestHandler(*Clipboard, OBJECTPTR Requester, int Item, BYTE Datatypes[4])</code></p>
<p>The callback is expected to send a <code>DATA::RECEIPT</code> to the object referenced by <code>Requester</code>.  The receipt must cover <code>Item</code> and use one of the preferred datatypes supplied in <code>Datatypes</code>.  If the request cannot be fulfilled, the callback should return <code>ERR::NoSupport</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="CEF">
      <const name="DELETE">Requests that the original file source is deleted if a successful paste operation takes place.</const>
      <const name="EXTEND">Instead of replacing existing clipboard data, add the new data to the group.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="CLIPTYPE" comment="Clipboard types">
      <const name="AUDIO">An audio clip that is recognised by the Sound class (such as wav's and mp3's).</const>
      <const name="DATA">Raw information that is uncategorised can be defined as a data clip.</const>
      <const name="FILE">Pure file references are stored as file clips.  This type is typically used by file managers for moving and copying files.</const>
      <const name="IMAGE">Images that are recognised by the Picture class may be stored as this type (such as jpeg's and png files).</const>
      <const name="OBJECT">An object that has been deserialised into binary form.</const>
      <const name="TEXT">Plain text files such as ASCII and UTF-8 must be identified through this clip type.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="CPF" comment="Clipboard flags">
      <const name="DRAG_DROP">Enables drag and drop mode.  The clipboard content will be private and not share data with the host system in this mode.</const>
      <const name="HISTORY_BUFFER">Enables the history buffer.  Note that this results in active clipboard monitoring and the program will make copies of all potential clipboard content - whether it is used or not.</const>
      <const name="HOST">This indicator is automatically set when a clipboard was created due to incoming content from the host system.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
