<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>Display</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Display</module>
    <comment>Represents a drawable display target and its host window or video mode.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>39413236</id>
    <idstring>DISPLAY</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2003-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>A Display object owns the bitmap-backed area that is presented to the user.  Depending on the active display driver, the object may represent a hosted desktop window, a native full-screen video mode or a platform-managed rendering surface.</p>
<p>Display is a low-level interface for display mode, window and bitmap management.  Most application code should create and manipulate <class name="Surface">Surface</class> objects instead, using Display directly only when it needs to configure the underlying window, display mode, palette, gamma or hardware-facing bitmap.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file>class_display.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Activate</name>
      <comment>Shows the display.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acActivate(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acActivate()</tiriPrototype>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Clear</name>
      <comment>Clears the display's drawable image data.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acClear(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acClear()</tiriPrototype>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Disable</name>
      <comment>Disables the display (goes into power saving mode).</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDisable(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDisable()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Disabling a display requests display power management, where supported by the active driver.  The DPMS mode is determined by user and system configuration.  The display remains disabled until <action>Enable</action> is called or the platform restores it.</p>
<p>This action does nothing if the display is in hosted mode.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">The display was disabled.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">The display driver does not support DPMS.</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Draw</name>
      <comment>Draws object graphics to drawable areas.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDraw(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDraw(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">The X position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">The Y position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">The width of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">The height of the region to be drawn.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Enable</name>
      <comment>Restores the display from power saving mode.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acEnable(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acEnable()</tiriPrototype>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Flush</name>
      <comment>Flushes pending graphics operations to the display driver.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acFlush(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acFlush()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Flush synchronises pending X11 requests or flushes OpenGL ES commands where those backends are active.  On other drivers it is a harmless no-op.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Focus</name>
      <comment>Focus on this object in the user interface.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acFocus(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acFocus()</tiriPrototype>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>GetKey</name>
      <comment>Retrieves formatted display information.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acGetKey(*Object, CSTRING Key, STRING Value, INT Size)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acGetKey(Key:str, Value:str, Size:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="CSTRING" name="Key">The name of a key value.</param>
        <param type="STRING" name="Value">Pointer to a buffer space large enough to hold the retrieved value.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Size">Indicates the byte size of the Buffer.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>GetKey currently supports the <code>resolution(Index, Format)</code> key.  <code>Index</code> selects a display resolution and <code>Format</code> is a string containing replacement tokens.  Supported tokens are <code>%w</code> for width, <code>%h</code> for height, <code>%d</code> for bit depth, <code>%c</code> for colour count and <code>%%</code> for a literal percent sign.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
        <error code="NoData">No data is available for use</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="OutOfRange">A value is outside of the valid range</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Hide</name>
      <comment>Hides a display from the user's view.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acHide(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acHide()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Hide removes a hosted display window from view, or releases the visible presentation resources used by native and OpenGL ES drivers.  The display remains valid and can be shown again with <action>Show</action>.</p>
<p>The <code>SCR::VISIBLE</code> flag is cleared after the hide request is processed.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Move</name>
      <comment>Moves the display by a relative offset.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMove(*Object, DOUBLE DeltaX, DOUBLE DeltaY, DOUBLE DeltaZ)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMove(DeltaX:num, DeltaY:num, DeltaZ:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaX">The number of units to move along the X axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaY">The number of units to move along the Y axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaZ">The number of units to move along the Z axis.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Move adjusts the hosted window or native display position by the supplied delta values.  Hosted drivers interpret the movement in window-manager coordinates.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="SystemCall">A call to the host system has failed</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToBack</name>
      <comment>Moves the hosted display window behind other windows.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToBack(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToBack()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>This action lowers the host window where the active platform supports window stacking.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToFront</name>
      <comment>Moves the hosted display window in front of other windows.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToFront(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToFront()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>This action raises the host window where the active platform supports window stacking.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToPoint</name>
      <comment>Move the display to a new position.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToPoint(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Z, MTF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToPoint(X:num, Y:num, Z:num, Flags:MTF)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">The new X position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">The new Y position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Z">The new Z position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="MTF" name="Flags" lookup="MTF">Set the relevant MTF flag for each provided parameter.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>MoveToPoint moves the display to an absolute position.  The <code>MTF::X</code> and <code>MTF::Y</code> flags determine which coordinates are applied.</p>
<p>In a hosted environment, the supplied coordinates describe the host window position.  The <fl>LeftMargin</fl> and <fl>TopMargin</fl> fields can be used when translating between host window coordinates and client-area coordinates.</p>
<p>For full-screen displays, MoveToPoint can alter the screen position for the hardware device managing the display output.  This is a rare feature that requires hardware support.  <code>ERR::NoSupport</code> is returned if this feature is unavailable.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="SystemCall">A call to the host system has failed</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Redimension</name>
      <comment>Moves and resizes a display object in a single action call.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acRedimension(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Z, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DOUBLE Depth)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acRedimension(X:num, Y:num, Z:num, Width:num, Height:num, Depth:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">The new X position to apply to the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">The new Y position to apply to the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Z">The new Z position to apply to the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">The new width of the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">The new height of the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Depth">The new depth of the target object.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Resize</name>
      <comment>Resizes the dimensions of a display object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acResize(*Object, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DOUBLE Depth)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acResize(Width:num, Height:num, Depth:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">The new width of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">The new height of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Depth">The new depth of the object.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Resize changes the display viewport size and resizes the underlying <fl>Bitmap</fl>.  If a display buffer is active, it is reallocated after the resize.</p>
<p>For hosted displays, <code>Width</code> and <code>Height</code> describe the client area inside the host window, not the full outer window including frame decorations.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="NotInitialised">The resource has not been initialised</error>
        <error code="Resize">Failure during the resize of an object</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>SaveImage</name>
      <comment>Saves the display bitmap image to a data object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acSaveImage(*Object, OBJECTID Dest, CLASSID ClassID)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acSaveImage(Dest:obj, ClassID:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="OBJECTID" name="Dest">Refers to an object that will receive the encoded image data.</param>
        <param type="CLASSID" name="ClassID">The Picture class to use for encoding the image data.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>SaveSettings</name>
      <comment>Saves the current display settings as defaults.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acSaveSettings(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acSaveSettings()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>SaveSettings stores supported window and display preferences, such as window position, size, DPMS setting and full-screen state, in the user display configuration.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="CreateObject">A call to CreateObject() failed</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Show</name>
      <comment>Presents a display object to the user.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acShow(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acShow()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Show presents a display object to the user.  On hosted platforms this maps or shows the host window.  By default the window uses the platform's normal border, title and window controls.  The initial window position is determined by the <fl>X</fl> and <fl>Y</fl> fields.  On native full-screen drivers, showing the display may switch the active video mode and present the display <fl>Bitmap</fl> across the screen.</p>
<p>If <code>SCR::BORDERLESS</code> is set in <fl>Flags</fl>, the host window is created without the normal window border and controls where the platform supports that mode.</p>
<p>In Microsoft Windows, the <fl>LeftMargin</fl>, <fl>RightMargin</fl>, <fl>TopMargin</fl> and <fl>BottomMargin</fl> fields will be updated to reflect the position of the client area within the hosted window.  In X11 these field values are all set to zero.</p>
<p>If the window is minimised at the time this action is called, the window will be restored to its original position if the code for the host platform supports this capability.</p>
<p>The <code>SCR::VISIBLE</code> flag is set if the Show operation succeeds.  Showing the first display also ensures that the shared <code>SystemPointer</code> object exists.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
      </result>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <methods>
    <method>
      <name>Minimise</name>
      <comment>Minimise the desktop window hosting the display.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::Minimise(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Minimise()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>If a display is hosted in a desktop window, Minimise() performs the platform's default minimise action for that window. On Microsoft Windows this normally minimises the window to the taskbar.  On X11 the current implementation unmaps the window.</p>
<p>Calling Minimise() on a display that is already minimised may restore the host window on some platforms.  Treat that behaviour as platform dependent.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SetDisplay</name>
      <comment>Changes the current display mode.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::SetDisplay(OBJECTPTR Object, INT X, INT Y, INT Width, INT Height, INT InsideWidth, INT InsideHeight, INT BitsPerPixel, DOUBLE RefreshRate, INT Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SetDisplay(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num, InsideWidth:num, InsideHeight:num, BitsPerPixel:num, RefreshRate:num, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">Horizontal offset of the display, relative to its default position.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">Vertical offset of the display, relative to its default position.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">Width of the display.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">Height of the display.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="InsideWidth">Internal display width (must be equal to or greater than the display width).</param>
        <param type="INT" name="InsideHeight">Internal display height (must be equal to or greater than the display height).</param>
        <param type="INT" name="BitsPerPixel">The desired display depth (15, 16, 24 or 32).</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="RefreshRate">Refresh rate, measured in floating point format for precision.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Flags">Optional flags.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>SetDisplay() changes the active display mode or hosted display size, depending on the platform.  It can alter display position, viewport dimensions, bit depth and refresh rate when the active display driver supports those features.  The new settings are applied immediately, although the graphics card, monitor or host window manager may introduce a short delay.</p>
<p>To keep any of the display settings at their current value, set the appropriate parameters to zero to leave them unchanged.  Only the parameters that you set will be used.</p>
<p>If a requested full-screen mode is not available, the driver may choose the closest supported mode.</p>
<p>Only the original owner of the display object is allowed to change the display settings.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Failed">Failed to switch to the requested display mode.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="Resize">Failure during the resize of an object</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SetGamma</name>
      <comment>Sets the display gamma levels.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::SetGamma(OBJECTPTR Object, DOUBLE Red, DOUBLE Green, DOUBLE Blue, GMF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SetGamma(Red:num, Green:num, Blue:num, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Red">Gamma correction for the red gun.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Green">Gamma correction for the green gun.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Blue">Gamma correction for the blue gun.</param>
        <param type="GMF" name="Flags" lookup="GMF">Optional flags.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>The SetGamma method controls the gamma correction levels for the display.  Gamma levels for the red, green and blue colour components can be set at floating point precision.  The default gamma level for each component is 1.0; the minimum value is 0.0 and the maximum value is 100.</p>
<p>Optional flags include <code>GMF::SAVE</code>.  This option stores the requested gamma values on the Display object so they can be saved as defaults where the driver supports persistent display settings.</p>
<p>If you would like to know the default gamma correction settings for a display, please refer to the <fl>Gamma</fl> field.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">The graphics hardware does not support gamma correction.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SetGammaLinear</name>
      <comment>Sets the display gamma level using a linear algorithm.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::SetGammaLinear(OBJECTPTR Object, DOUBLE Red, DOUBLE Green, DOUBLE Blue, GMF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SetGammaLinear(Red:num, Green:num, Blue:num, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Red">New red gamma value.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Green">New green gamma value.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Blue">New blue gamma value.</param>
        <param type="GMF" name="Flags" lookup="GMF">Use <code>SAVE</code> to store the new settings.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>SetGammaLinear() updates display gamma values with a linear algorithm where the active driver supports it.  Values are clamped to the supported range before being applied.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SetMonitor</name>
      <comment>Changes the default monitor settings.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::SetMonitor(OBJECTPTR Object, CSTRING Name, INT MinH, INT MaxH, INT MinV, INT MaxV, MON Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SetMonitor(Name:str, MinH:num, MaxH:num, MinV:num, MaxV:num, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="CSTRING" name="Name">The name of the display.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="MinH">The minimum horizontal scan rate.  Usually set to 31.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="MaxH">The maximum horizontal scan rate.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="MinV">The minimum vertical scan rate.  Usually set to 50.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="MaxV">The maximum vertical scan rate.</param>
        <param type="MON" name="Flags" lookup="MON">Set to <code>AUTO_DETECT</code> if the monitor settings should be auto-detected on startup.  Set <code>BIT_6</code> if the device is limited to 6-bit colour output.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Use SetMonitor() to change the monitor metadata and scan-rate limits used by native display drivers.  Altering the supported frequencies can change the available display resolutions and maximum refresh rate.</p>
<p>The auto-detect option requests monitor detection when the desktop starts.  If detection fails, the system reverts to its default monitor settings.</p>
<p>This method does not work on hosted platforms.  All parameters passed to this method are optional (set a value to zero if it should not be changed).</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
        <error code="NoPermission">General security violation</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SizeHints</name>
      <comment>Sets the width and height restrictions for the host window (hosted environments only).</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::SizeHints(OBJECTPTR Object, INT MinWidth, INT MinHeight, INT MaxWidth, INT MaxHeight, INT EnforceAspect)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SizeHints(MinWidth:num, MinHeight:num, MaxWidth:num, MaxHeight:num, EnforceAspect:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="MinWidth">The minimum width of the window.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="MinHeight">The minimum height of the window.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="MaxWidth">The maximum width of the window.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="MaxHeight">The maximum height of the window.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="EnforceAspect">Set to true to enforce an aspect ratio that is scaled from MinWidth,MinHeight to MaxWidth,MaxHeight.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>If a display is hosted in a desktop window, it may be possible to enforce size restrictions that prevent the window from being shrunk or expanded beyond a certain size.  This feature is platform dependent and <code>ERR::NoSupport</code> will be returned if it is not implemented.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">The host platform does not support this feature.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>UpdatePalette</name>
      <comment>Updates the video display palette to new colour values if in 256 colour mode.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::UpdatePalette(OBJECTPTR Object, struct RGBPalette * NewPalette)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = UpdatePalette(NewPalette:any)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="struct RGBPalette *" name="NewPalette">The new palette to apply to the display bitmap.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Call UpdatePalette() to copy a new palette to the display bitmap's internal palette.  If the video display is running in 256-colour mode, the new palette colours are also applied to the display where supported.</p>
<p>This method has no visible effect on RGB pixel displays.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>WaitVBL</name>
      <comment>Waits for a vertical blank.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR gfx::WaitVBL(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = WaitVBL()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>WaitVBL() waits for the display to reach vertical blank where the active driver exposes that timing primitive.  Drivers that do not support it return <code>ERR::NoSupport</code> immediately.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">Operation not supported</error>
      </result>
    </method>

  </methods>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Bitmap</name>
      <comment>Reference to the display's bitmap information.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type class="Bitmap">*Bitmap</type>
      <description>
<p>The <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> object describes the drawable pixel region presented by the display.  It stores the width, height, colour format, palette and related bitmap state.  Display fields mirror the most common bitmap dimensions, so callers rarely need to access the bitmap directly for simple sizing operations.</p>
<p>The <class name="Bitmap" field="Width">Bitmap.Width</class> and <class name="Bitmap" field="Height">Bitmap.Height</class> can be larger than the visible display area, but never smaller.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BmpX</name>
      <comment>The horizontal coordinate of the bitmap within a display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field stores the horizontal offset of the <fl>Bitmap</fl> relative to the visible display viewport.  It is used by drivers that support a bitmap larger than the visible display area.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BmpY</name>
      <comment>The vertical coordinate of the Bitmap within a display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field stores the vertical offset of the <fl>Bitmap</fl> relative to the visible display viewport.  It is used by drivers that support a bitmap larger than the visible display area.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BottomMargin</name>
      <comment>In hosted mode, indicates the bottom margin of the client window.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>If the display is hosted in a client window, the BottomMargin indicates the number of pixels between the client area and the bottom window edge.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Chipset</name>
      <comment>String describing the graphics chipset.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>This string describes the graphic card's chipset, if known.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Display</name>
      <comment>String describing the display (e.g. model name of the monitor).</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>This string describes the display device that is connected to the user's graphics card.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DisplayManufacturer</name>
      <comment>String describing the display manufacturer.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>This string names the manufacturer of the user's display device.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DisplayType</name>
      <comment>Identifies the active display backend.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type lookup="DT">DT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field reports the display driver type, such as native, X11, Windows GDI or OpenGL ES.</p>
<types lookup="DT"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Flags</name>
      <comment>Optional flag settings.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="SCR">SCR</type>
      <description>
<p>Display flags configure hosted-window behaviour, buffering, visibility, controller grabbing and driver-reported capabilities.  After initialisation, only a limited subset can be changed and support for changing window style is platform dependent.</p>
<types lookup="SCR"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Gamma</name>
      <comment>Contains red, green and blue values for the display's gamma setting.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE []</type>
      <description>
<p>The gamma settings for the display are stored in this field.  The settings are stored in an array of 3 floating point values that represent the red, green and blue colour components.  The default gamma value for each component is 1.0.</p>
<p>To modify the display gamma values, please refer to the <method>SetGamma</method> and <method>SetGammaLinear</method> methods.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>HDensity</name>
      <comment>Returns the horizontal pixel density for the display.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Reading the HDensity field will return the horizontal pixel density for the display (pixels per inch).  If the physical size of the display is unknown, a default value based on the platform is returned.  For standard desktop systems this will usually be 96.</p>
<p>A custom density value can be enforced by setting the <code>/interface/@dpi</code> value in the loaded style, or by setting HDensity.</p>
<p>Reading this field always succeeds.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Height</name>
      <comment>Defines the height of the display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines the visible display viewport height.  If the height exceeds allowable limits, it is restricted to a value that the display driver can handle.</p>
<p>If the display is hosted, the height reflects the internal height of the host window.  On some hosted systems, the true height of the window can be calculated by reading the <fl>TopMargin</fl> and <fl>BottomMargin</fl> fields.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>InsideHeight</name>
      <comment>Represents the internal height of the display.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>On drivers that support a drawable area larger than the visible viewport, InsideHeight reflects the internal bitmap height in pixels.  If this feature is not in use, InsideHeight is equal to <fl>Height</fl>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>InsideWidth</name>
      <comment>Represents the internal width of the display.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>On drivers that support a drawable area larger than the visible viewport, InsideWidth reflects the internal bitmap width in pixels.  If this feature is not in use, InsideWidth is equal to <fl>Width</fl>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>LeftMargin</name>
      <comment>In hosted mode, indicates the left-hand margin of the client window.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>If the display is hosted in a client window, the LeftMargin indicates the number of pixels between the client area and the left window edge.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Manufacturer</name>
      <comment>String describing the manufacturer of the graphics hardware.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>The string in this field returns the name of the manufacturer that created the user's graphics card.  If this information is not detectable, a <code>NULL</code> pointer is returned.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MaxHScan</name>
      <comment>The maximum horizontal scan rate of the display output device.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>If the display output device supports variable refresh rates, this field will refer to the maximum horizontal scan rate supported by the device.  If variable refresh rates are not supported, this field is set to zero.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MaxVScan</name>
      <comment>The maximum vertical scan rate of the display output device.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>If the display output device supports variable refresh rates, this field will refer to the maximum vertical scan rate supported by the device.  If variable refresh rates are not supported, this field is set to zero.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MinHScan</name>
      <comment>The minimum horizontal scan rate of the display output device.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>If the display output device supports variable refresh rates, this field will refer to the minimum horizontal scan rate supported by the device.  If variable refresh rates are not supported, this field is set to zero.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MinVScan</name>
      <comment>The minimum vertical scan rate of the display output device.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>If the display output device supports variable refresh rates, this field will refer to the minimum vertical scan rate supported by the device.  If variable refresh rates are not supported, this field is set to zero.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Opacity</name>
      <comment>Determines the level of translucency applied to the display window (hosted displays only).</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field determines the translucency level applied to a hosted display window, expressed as a normalised value.  The default setting is 1, which makes the display fully opaque.  Lower values make the window more transparent where the host platform supports translucent windows.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>PopOver</name>
      <comment>Enables pop-over support for hosted display windows.</comment>
      <access write="S">Set</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>The PopOver field can be used when a display is hosted as a window.  Setting the PopOver field to refer to the object ID of another display will ensure that the host window is always in front of the other display's window (assuming both windows are visible on the desktop).</p>
<p>The <code>ERR::NoSupport</code> error code is returned if the host does not support this functionality or if the display owns the output device.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>PowerMode</name>
      <comment>The display's power management method.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type lookup="DPMS">DPMS</type>
      <description>
<p>When DPMS is supported and <action>Disable</action> is called, this field identifies the requested power-management mode.</p>
<p>DPMS is normally user-configurable, so applications should avoid changing PowerMode without user intent.</p>
<types lookup="DPMS"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>RefreshRate</name>
      <comment>Active display refresh rate.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field reflects the refresh rate of the currently active full-screen display mode where the driver can report it. Hosted display drivers may leave this value unset or set it to a sentinel value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ResizeFeedback</name>
      <comment>Callback invoked when the display position or size changes.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>FUNCTION</type>
      <description>
<p>Set this field to receive display resize feedback from hosted-window events and display-managed coordinate repairs. The callback receives the display object ID, X, Y, Width and Height values.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>RightMargin</name>
      <comment>In hosted mode, indicates the pixel margin between the client window and right window edge.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Title</name>
      <comment>Sets the window title (hosted environments only).</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>TopMargin</name>
      <comment>In hosted mode, indicates the pixel margin between the client window and top window edge.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>TotalMemory</name>
      <comment>The total amount of user accessible RAM installed on the video card, or zero if unknown.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>TotalResolutions</name>
      <comment>The total number of resolutions supported by the display.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>VDensity</name>
      <comment>Returns the vertical pixel density for the display.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Reading the VDensity field will return the vertical pixel density for the display (pixels per inch).  If the physical size of the display is unknown, a default value based on the platform is returned.  For standard desktop systems this will usually be 96.</p>
<p>A custom density value can be enforced by setting the <code>/interface/@dpi</code> value in the loaded style, or by setting VDensity.</p>
<p>Reading this field always succeeds.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Width</name>
      <comment>Defines the width of the display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines the visible display viewport width.  If the width exceeds allowable limits, it is restricted to a value that the display driver can handle.</p>
<p>If the display is hosted, the width reflects the internal width of the host window.  On some hosted systems, the true width of the window can be calculated by reading the <fl>LeftMargin</fl> and <fl>RightMargin</fl> fields.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>WindowHandle</name>
      <comment>Refers to a display object's window handle, if relevant.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>APTR</type>
      <description>
<p>This field refers to the platform window handle owned or used by the display.  It is relevant only on hosted display backends such as X11 and Microsoft Windows.</p>
<p>Set WindowHandle before initialisation to bind the Display object to an existing host window.  In that case the display sets <code>SCR::CUSTOM_WINDOW</code> and will not destroy the host window as its own resource.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>X</name>
      <comment>Defines the horizontal coordinate of the display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The X field defines the horizontal coordinate of the display.  On native full-screen drivers this is a hardware offset and should normally remain zero unless the output device requires adjustment.</p>
<p>On hosted displays, prior to initialisation the coordinate will reflect the position of the display window when it is created.  After initialisation, the coordinate is altered to reflect the absolute position of the client area of the display window.  The <fl>LeftMargin</fl> can be used to determine the actual position of the host window.</p>
<p>To adjust the position of the display, use the <action>MoveToPoint</action> action rather than setting this field directly.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Y</name>
      <comment>Defines the vertical coordinate of the display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The Y field defines the vertical coordinate of the display.  On native full-screen drivers this is a hardware offset and should normally remain zero unless the output device requires adjustment.</p>
<p>On hosted displays, prior to initialisation the coordinate will reflect the position of the display window when it is created.  After initialisation, the coordinate is altered to reflect the absolute position of the client area of the display window.  The <fl>TopMargin</fl> can be used to determine the actual position of the host window.</p>
<p>To adjust the position of the display, use the <action>MoveToPoint</action> action rather than setting this field directly.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="DPMS" comment="Possible modes for the Display class' PowerMode field.">
      <const name="DEFAULT">Use the default DPMS mode as defined by the display driver.</const>
      <const name="OFF">Stop sending power to the display in order to turn it off (it may not be possible to restart the display without the user's intervention).</const>
      <const name="STANDBY">Puts the display into standby (reduced power) mode.</const>
      <const name="SUSPEND">Puts the display into suspend mode (blanks the display output while maintaining normal power levels).</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="DT" comment="Flags for GetDisplayType().">
      <const name="GLES">The display is driven by OpenGLES.</const>
      <const name="NATIVE">The display is native (supported by internal drivers).</const>
      <const name="WINGDI">The display is driven by Microsoft Windows drivers.</const>
      <const name="X11">The display is driven by the X Window System (X11, X.Org, XFree86)</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="GMF" comment="Flags for gamma operations.">
      <const name="SAVE">Save the provided settings permanently.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="MON" comment="Flags for the Display class SetMonitor() method.">
      <const name="AUTO_DETECT">Monitor settings to be auto-detected on startup.</const>
      <const name="BIT_6">The device is limited to 6-bit colour production in real terms.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="SCR" comment="Display flags.">
      <const name="ACTIVE">The display is participating in the desktop view - but does not guarantee it is visible.</const>
      <const name="ALPHA_BLEND">Enables alpha channel blending (if display is hosted and 32-bit).</const>
      <const name="AUTO_SAVE">Saves settings to the global display state when the object is freed.</const>
      <const name="BIT_6">Display is limited to 6-bit output per colour gun.</const>
      <const name="BORDERLESS">If display is hosted, create it as a popup / borderless window.</const>
      <const name="BUFFER">Set if you would like a complementing buffer in video RAM.</const>
      <const name="COMPOSITE">Enables alpha channel blending (if display is hosted and 32-bit).</const>
      <const name="CUSTOM_WINDOW">The display has been created with a custom window reference.</const>
      <const name="DPMS_ENABLED">Power saving through DPMS is supported.</const>
      <const name="FLIPPABLE">If <code>SCR::BUFFER</code> is used, this flag may be set by the display manager if it is possible to flip the buffer.</const>
      <const name="GRAB_CONTROLLERS">Grab controllers for receiving input when the display has the focus.</const>
      <const name="GTF_ENABLED">GTF frequency timings are supported.</const>
      <const name="HOSTED">The display is a desktop hosted window.</const>
      <const name="MAXIMISE">Special win32 flag.</const>
      <const name="MAXSIZE">For <function module="Display">GetDisplayInfo</function> only, indicates that the width and height values indicate the display's maximum size.</const>
      <const name="MIRRORED">The display is a mirrored copy.</const>
      <const name="NO_ACCELERATION">2D graphics card acceleration is not available.</const>
      <const name="POWERSAVE">Power saving is active (read-only).</const>
      <const name="PRIMARY">The display is flagged as being the primary.</const>
      <const name="READ_ONLY">Synonym for <code>MAXIMISE | CUSTOM_WINDOW | FLIPPABLE | GTF_ENABLED | DPMS_ENABLED | POWERSAVE | HOSTED | MAXSIZE | REFRESH | BIT_6 | VISIBLE | NO_ACCELERATION</code></const>
      <const name="REFRESH">For <function module="Display">GetDisplayInfo</function> only, used to indicate that a display change has recently occurred and cache refresh is required.</const>
      <const name="ROTATED">True if the display is rotated.</const>
      <const name="VIRTUAL">The display is virtual or not visible (device not switched on).</const>
      <const name="VISIBLE">Set if the screen is on display.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
