<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>Surface</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Display</module>
    <comment>Manages display regions for two-dimensional rendered graphics.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>c6a69b5c</id>
    <idstring>SURFACE</idstring>
    <category>GUI</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2003-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The Surface class represents a rectangular region in the display hierarchy.  It manages positioning, visibility, redraws, backing storage and focus for layered user interfaces.  Surfaces work with <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> objects for rendered pixel data and with the <class name="Pointer">Pointer</class> class for pointer interaction.</p>
<p>A top-level surface is normally backed by an application window on hosted platforms such as Windows and Linux.  On native displays, full screen displays and Android, a top-level surface can cover the display without a separate host window.  Child surfaces are attached to a parent surface, creating a hierarchy whose ordering, clipping, redraw and input behaviour is managed by this class.</p>
<p>Surface-only interfaces are supported, but most applications should use surfaces as hosts for <class name="VectorScene">VectorScene</class> objects. This keeps interfaces resolution independent and matches the rendering path that Kōtuku optimises most heavily.</p>
<p>Surface content is preserved with a backing store where required.  Surfaces that share a backing store are composited through their parent, while surfaces that need independent redraw, opacity, video memory or cursor behaviour can own a separate bitmap buffer.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="class_surface/">class_surface.cpp</file>
      <file path="class_surface/">surface_dimensions.cpp</file>
      <file path="class_surface/">surface_drawing.cpp</file>
      <file path="class_surface/">surface_fields.cpp</file>
      <file path="class_surface/">surface_resize.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Activate</name>
      <comment>Shows a surface object on the display.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acActivate(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acActivate()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>For top-level surfaces, Activate() delegates to <action>Show</action> so that the hosted display window becomes visible.  Child surfaces are not affected by this action.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Disable</name>
      <comment>Disables a surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDisable(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDisable()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Disabled surfaces remain visible but cannot accept user focus through <action>Focus</action>.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Draw</name>
      <comment>Redraws the contents of a surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDraw(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDraw(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">The X position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">The Y position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">The width of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">The height of the region to be drawn.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Calling the Draw action on a surface object will send redraw messages to every hook that has been attached to the surface object's drawing system.  This has the effect of redrawing all graphics within the surface object.  The procedure is as follows:</p>
<list type="ordered">
<li>If the surface object's <fl>Colour</fl> field has been set, the target bitmap will be cleared to that colour.</li>
<li>If the surface is volatile, graphics from background surfaces will be copied to the  target bitmap.</li>
<li>Subscribers to the surface object are now called via their hooks so that they can draw to the bitmap.</li>
<li>The bitmap is copied to the video display buffer to complete the process.</li>
</list>
<p>Please be aware that:</p>
<list>
<li>If the target surface contains child surfaces, they will not be redrawn unless they are volatile (using special
effects such as transparency, or using the region flag will make a surface volatile).</li>
<li>If the surface object has not had its background colour set, or if the object is not volatile, the bitmap
contents will not be automatically cleared (this is advantageous in situations where a particular object will clear
the surface area first).</li>
</list>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Enable</name>
      <comment>Enables a disabled surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acEnable(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acEnable()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Enable() clears the disabled state so that the surface can receive focus and normal interaction again.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Focus</name>
      <comment>Changes the primary user focus to the surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acFocus(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acFocus()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Focus() makes the surface the primary focus target and notifies the affected focus subscribers.  Focus is propagated through the surface hierarchy so that parent surfaces also record inherited focus.</p>
<p>The request is ignored if the surface is disabled, marked with <code>RNF::NO_FOCUS</code>, or outside the active modal surface. If <code>RNF::IGNORE_FOCUS</code> is set, the focus request is forwarded to the parent surface instead.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Hide</name>
      <comment>Hides a surface object from the display.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acHide(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acHide()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Hide() clears the visible state.  For top-level surfaces it hides the hosted display window; for child surfaces it invalidates and exposes the covered parent area so that the background is redrawn.  Hiding a modal surface also restores the previous modal surface, or clears modal mode if there is no previous surface.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>LostFocus</name>
      <comment>Informs a surface object that it has lost the user focus.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acLostFocus(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acLostFocus()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>LostFocus() clears the <code>RNF::HAS_FOCUS</code> flag when the surface currently holds focus.  If the surface has already lost focus, the action returns without further notification.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Move</name>
      <comment>Moves a surface object to a new display position.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMove(*Object, DOUBLE DeltaX, DOUBLE DeltaY, DOUBLE DeltaZ)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMove(DeltaX:num, DeltaY:num, DeltaZ:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaX">The number of units to move along the X axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaY">The number of units to move along the Y axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaZ">The number of units to move along the Z axis.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Move() applies relative X and Y deltas to the surface.  The request honours movement restrictions such as <code>RNF::STICKY</code>, <code>RNF::NO_HORIZONTAL</code>, <code>RNF::NO_VERTICAL</code> and the configured movement limits.  Child surfaces are clamped within their parent surface when limits are active.</p>
<p>Queued Move() requests for the same surface may be combined before drawing occurs.  After a successful move, redimension subscribers are notified with the surface's updated position and size.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToBack</name>
      <comment>Moves a surface object to the back of its container.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToBack(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToBack()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>For child surfaces, MoveToBack() reorders the surface within its parent while preserving child hierarchy, bitmap ownership constraints, pop-over relationships and <code>RNF::STICK_TO_BACK</code> ordering.  Top-level surfaces delegate the request to their hosted display window.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToFront</name>
      <comment>Moves a surface object to the front of its container.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToFront(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToFront()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>For child surfaces, MoveToFront() raises the surface within its parent while preserving child hierarchy, cursor ordering, bitmap ownership constraints, pop-over relationships and <code>RNF::STICK_TO_FRONT</code> ordering.  Top-level surfaces delegate the request to their hosted display window.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToPoint</name>
      <comment>Moves a surface object to an absolute coordinate.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToPoint(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Z, MTF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToPoint(X:num, Y:num, Z:num, Flags:MTF)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">The new X position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">The new Y position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Z">The new Z position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="MTF" name="Flags" lookup="MTF">Set the relevant MTF flag for each provided parameter.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>MoveToPoint() converts the supplied absolute X and Y values into relative movement and forwards the request to <action>Move</action>.  Coordinates are changed only for axes enabled by the <code>MTF::X</code> and <code>MTF::Y</code> flags.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Redimension</name>
      <comment>Moves and resizes a surface object in a single action call.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acRedimension(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Z, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DOUBLE Depth)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acRedimension(X:num, Y:num, Z:num, Width:num, Height:num, Depth:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">The new X position to apply to the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">The new Y position to apply to the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Z">The new Z position to apply to the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">The new width of the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">The new height of the target object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Depth">The new depth of the target object.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Resize</name>
      <comment>Alters the dimensions of a surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acResize(*Object, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DOUBLE Depth)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acResize(Width:num, Height:num, Depth:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">The new width of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">The new height of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Depth">The new depth of the object.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>SaveImage</name>
      <comment>Saves the graphics of a surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acSaveImage(*Object, OBJECTID Dest, CLASSID ClassID)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acSaveImage(Dest:obj, ClassID:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="OBJECTID" name="Dest">Refers to an object that will receive the encoded image data.</param>
        <param type="CLASSID" name="ClassID">The Picture class to use for encoding the image data.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>SaveImage() renders the visible content of a surface into an image and writes it to the destination object supplied in the action arguments.  Visible child surfaces in the captured region are included in the resulting image.</p>
<p>The image format is selected with the <code>ClassID</code> argument.  Supported values are <class name="Picture">Picture</class>-compatible image classes such as <code>CLASSID::JPEG</code> and <code>CLASSID::PICTURE</code> (PNG).  If <code>ClassID</code> is <code>CLASSID::NIL</code>, the default <class name="Picture">Picture</class> implementation is used.</p>
<p>Errors returned while copying individual child surfaces can be propagated from <function>CopySurface</function>.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Failed">The intermediate picture object could not be initialised or saved.</error>
        <error code="Search">A search routine in this function failed</error>
        <error code="AccessObject">Attempting to lock an object failed</error>
        <error code="NewObject">The intermediate picture object could not be created.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Show</name>
      <comment>Shows a surface object on the display.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acShow(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acShow()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Show() makes the surface visible.  For top-level surfaces it shows the hosted display window; for child surfaces it sets the visible flag, redraws the surface and exposes the affected area.  If the surface is modal, it becomes the active modal surface until it is hidden.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <methods>
    <method>
      <name>AddCallback</name>
      <comment>Inserts a function hook into the drawing process of a surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::AddCallback(OBJECTPTR Object, FUNCTION * Callback)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = AddCallback(Callback:func)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="FUNCTION *" name="Callback">Callback routine to insert or move in the draw callback list.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>The AddCallback() method installs a draw callback for custom rendering directly into a surface.  During a redraw, callbacks are invoked in subscription order and receive the target <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> for the surface.</p>
<p>The C/C++ callback prototype is <code>ERR Function(APTR Context, objSurface *Surface, objBitmap *Bitmap, APTR Meta)</code>. The Tiri callback prototype is <code>function draw(Surface, Bitmap)</code>.</p>
<p>Callbacks may draw to the bitmap as they would to any other <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class>.  Use the Surface <fl>Width</fl> and <fl>Height</fl> fields to determine the drawable area, and respect the bitmap clipping region when writing pixels directly.</p>
<p>Calling AddCallback() with a callback that is already registered for the same object moves that callback to the end of the callback list, making it run after the callbacks that remain before it.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoPermission">Public objects cannot draw directly to surfaces.</error>
        <error code="ArrayFull">The callback list has reached its maximum size.</error>
        <error code="AllocMemory">The callback list could not be expanded.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>ExposeToDisplay</name>
      <comment>Redraws a surface region to the display, preferably from its graphics buffer.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::ExposeToDisplay(OBJECTPTR Object, INT X, INT Y, INT Width, INT Height, EXF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = ExposeToDisplay(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">X coordinate of the expose area.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">Y coordinate of the expose area.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">Width of the expose area.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">Height of the expose area.</param>
        <param type="EXF" name="Flags" lookup="EXF">Optional flags.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Call the ExposeToDisplay() method to copy a surface region to the display.  The functionality is identical to that of the <function module="Surface">ExposeSurface</function> function.  Please refer to it for further documentation.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>InvalidateRegion</name>
      <comment>Redraws all of the content in a surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::InvalidateRegion(OBJECTPTR Object, INT X, INT Y, INT Width, INT Height)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = InvalidateRegion(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">X coordinate of the region to invalidate.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">Y coordinate of the region to invalidate.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">Width of the region to invalidate.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">Height of the region to invalidate.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Invalidating a surface object will cause everything within a specified area to be redrawn.  This includes child surface objects that intersect with the area that you have specified.  Parent regions that overlap are not included in the redraw.</p>
<p>To quickly redraw an entire surface object's content, call this method directly without supplying an argument structure. If you want to redraw a surface object and ignore all of its surface children then you should use the Draw action instead of this method.</p>
<p>If you want to refresh a surface area to the display then you should use the <method>ExposeToDisplay</method> method instead.  Exposing will use the graphics buffer to refresh the graphics, thus avoiding the speed loss of a complete redraw.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="AccessMemory">Failed to access the internal surface list.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>Minimise</name>
      <comment>For hosted surfaces only, this method will minimise the surface to an icon.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::Minimise(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Minimise()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>If a surface is hosted in a desktop window, calling Minimise() performs the host platform's default minimise action on that window.  On Microsoft Windows, this normally minimises the window to the taskbar.</p>
<p>Calling Minimise() on a surface that is already in the minimised state may result in the host window being restored to the desktop.  This behaviour is platform dependent and should be manually tested to confirm its reliability on the host platform.</p>
      </description>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>RemoveCallback</name>
      <comment>Removes a callback previously inserted by AddCallback().</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::RemoveCallback(OBJECTPTR Object, FUNCTION * Callback)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = RemoveCallback(Callback:func)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="FUNCTION *" name="Callback">Callback routine to remove, or <code>NULL</code> to remove all associated callback routines for the caller.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>RemoveCallback() removes a draw callback that was previously inserted by <method>AddCallback</method>.</p>
<p>This method is scope restricted.  A caller can remove only callbacks associated with its own object context, so callbacks added by other objects are not affected.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Search">The requested callback was not found.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>ResetDimensions</name>
      <comment>Changes the dimensions of a surface.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::ResetDimensions(OBJECTPTR Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE XOffset, DOUBLE YOffset, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DMF Dimensions)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = ResetDimensions(X:num, Y:num, XOffset:num, YOffset:num, Width:num, Height:num, Dimensions:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">New X coordinate.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">New Y coordinate.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="XOffset">New X offset.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="YOffset">New Y offset.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">New width.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">New height.</param>
        <param type="DMF" name="Dimensions" lookup="DMF">Dimension flags.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>ResetDimensions() replaces the dimensional declaration used by a surface.  Use this when the relationship between fields changes, for example when a width previously derived from <code>X</code> and <code>XOffset</code> must become a fixed width.</p>
<p>It is not necessary to define a value for every parameter - only the ones that are relevant to the new dimension settings.  For example, if <code>X</code> and <code>Width</code> are set, <code>XOffset</code> is ignored and the <code>Dimensions</code> value must include <code>DMF::FIXED_X</code> and <code>DMF::FIXED_WIDTH</code> or their scaled equivalents.  Refer to the <fl>Dimensions</fl> field for the supported dimension flags.</p>
<p>After the new dimensions are applied, the union of the old and new areas is redrawn and exposed.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>ScheduleRedraw</name>
      <comment>Schedules a redraw operation for the next frame.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::ScheduleRedraw(OBJECTPTR Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = ScheduleRedraw()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Use ScheduleRedraw() to mark a surface for redraw on the next frame cycle.  The surface and its child surfaces are redrawn together, typically on the next 1/60th of a second timer tick.  Direct redraw requests for the target surface are coalesced until the scheduled redraw is processed.</p>
<p>Scheduling is ideal in situations where a cluster of redraw events may occur within a tight time period, and it would be inefficient to draw those changes to the display individually.</p>
<p>Redraw schedules do not merge across the hierarchy.  If both a surface and one of its children are scheduled, two redraw operations may be triggered where one would otherwise suffice.  Schedule the highest relevant surface when a single redraw should cover a group of changes.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Failed">General failure</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SetDisplay</name>
      <comment>Changes the screen resolution (applies to top-level surface objects only).</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::SetDisplay(OBJECTPTR Object, INT X, INT Y, INT Width, INT Height, INT InsideWidth, INT InsideHeight, INT BitsPerPixel, DOUBLE RefreshRate, INT Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SetDisplay(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num, InsideWidth:num, InsideHeight:num, BitsPerPixel:num, RefreshRate:num, Flags:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">The horizontal coordinate/offset for the display.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">The vertical coordinate/offset for the display.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">The width of the display.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">The height of the display.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="InsideWidth">The page width of the display must be the same as Width or greater.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="InsideHeight">The page height of the display must be the same as Height or greater.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="BitsPerPixel">Bits per pixel - 15, 16, 24 or 32.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="RefreshRate">Refresh rate.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Flags">Optional flags.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>The SetDisplay method is used to change the screen resolution of the top-level surface object (which represents the screen display).  It allows you to set the size of the display and you may also change the bitmap depth and the monitor's refresh rate.  If successful, the change is immediate.</p>
<p>This method exercises some intelligence in adjusting the display to your requested settings.  For instance, if the requested width and/or height is not available, the closest display setting will be chosen.</p>
<p>This method does not work on anything other than top-level surface objects.  The current top-level surface object is usually named &quot;SystemSurface&quot; by default and can be searched for by that name.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
        <error code="InvalidState">The surface is not a top-level surface object.</error>
      </result>
    </method>

    <method>
      <name>SetOpacity</name>
      <comment>Alters the opacity of a surface object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR drw::SetOpacity(OBJECTPTR Object, DOUBLE Value, DOUBLE Adjustment)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = SetOpacity(Value:num, Adjustment:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Value">New opacity multiplier, used when <code>Adjustment</code> is zero.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Adjustment">Value to add to the current opacity multiplier, or zero to assign <code>Value</code> directly.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>SetOpacity() changes the opacity multiplier for a surface that owns its bitmap buffer.  The final value is clamped by the <fl>Opacity</fl> field setter.  If the surface is visible, a redraw is queued so the new opacity is reflected on the display without blocking the caller.</p>
      </description>
      <result>
        <error code="Okay">Operation successful.</error>
        <error code="NoSupport">The surface does not own the bitmap buffer required for independent opacity.</error>
        <error code="NullArgs">Function call missing argument value(s)</error>
      </result>
    </method>

  </methods>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>AbsX</name>
      <comment>The absolute horizontal position of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field returns the surface's horizontal position relative to the top-level surface in its local hierarchy.</p>
<p>Writing <code>AbsX</code> moves the surface so that its absolute horizontal position matches the supplied value.  The surface must be initialised before this field can be changed.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>AbsY</name>
      <comment>The absolute vertical position of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field returns the surface's vertical position relative to the top-level surface in its local hierarchy.</p>
<p>Writing <code>AbsY</code> moves the surface so that its absolute vertical position matches the supplied value.  The surface must be initialised before this field can be changed.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Align</name>
      <comment>This field allows you to align a surface area within its owner.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type lookup="ALIGN">ALIGN</type>
      <description>
<p>Use <code>Align</code> to position a surface within its owner without calculating explicit coordinates.  It is most useful for horizontal or vertical centring; edge alignment is normally clearer when expressed through <fl>X</fl>, <fl>Y</fl>, <fl>XOffset</fl> and <fl>YOffset</fl>.</p>
<p>Setting <code>Align</code> replaces related coordinate settings.  Valid alignment flags are <code>BOTTOM</code>, <code>CENTER</code>, <code>MIDDLE</code>, <code>LEFT</code>, <code>HORIZONTAL</code>, <code>RIGHT</code>, <code>TOP</code> and <code>VERTICAL</code>.</p>
<types lookup="ALIGN"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BitsPerPixel</name>
      <comment>Defines the pixel depth used by the surface buffer.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>BitsPerPixel</code> before initialisation to request a fixed pixel depth for the surface buffer.  If the requested depth differs from the display or parent buffer, the graphics system converts pixels when the surface is drawn, which is usually slower than using the native display depth.</p>
<p>Reading this field returns the active tracked depth for the surface.  A value of zero is returned if the surface is not available in the display surface list.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Bottom</name>
      <comment>Returns the bottom-most coordinate of a surface object, <code>Y + Height</code>.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BottomLimit</name>
      <comment>Prevents a surface object from moving beyond a given point at the bottom of its container.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>BottomLimit</code> to reserve a margin at the bottom of the parent container.  For example, a value of <code>5</code> prevents <action>Move</action> from placing the surface inside the bottom-most five coordinate units.</p>
<p>Movement limits apply only to <action>Move</action>.  Direct writes to coordinate fields bypass them.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Buffer</name>
      <comment>Refers to the <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> that stores the surface's graphics.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>Each surface is assigned a bitmap buffer for drawing.  In many cases this buffer is shared between multiple surfaces, so clients should treat it as an implementation detail unless no public drawing API provides the required access.</p>
<p>The bitmap is an off-screen buffer.  Direct changes to it are not exposed to the display automatically.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Colour</name>
      <comment>Defines the background colour used when clearing the surface.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>RGB8</type>
      <description>
<p>Set this field when a surface should be cleared to a solid background colour before drawing.  String values may use <code>#RRGGBB</code> hexadecimal notation or <code>Red,Green,Blue</code> decimal components.</p>
<p>A surface that does not define a colour is not cleared during redraw.  In that case, draw the full background manually to avoid stale or uninitialised graphics appearing in exposed areas.</p>
<p>A preset colour can be disabled by writing <code>NULL</code>, which clears the colour by setting its alpha component to zero. Changing <code>Colour</code> does not schedule a redraw.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Cursor</name>
      <comment>Sets the pointer image used while the mouse is over the surface.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="PTC">PTC</type>
      <description>
<p>The pointer automatically switches to the selected cursor image when it enters the surface area.</p>
<p>The available cursor image settings are listed in the <class name="Pointer" field="CursorID">Pointer.CursorID</class> documentation.</p>
<p>The <code>Cursor</code> field may be written with a valid cursor name or cursor ID.</p>
<types lookup="PTC"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Dimensions</name>
      <comment>Indicates currently active dimension settings.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="DMF">DMF</type>
      <description>
<p>The <code>Dimensions</code> flags identify which coordinate and size fields currently define the surface layout, and whether those values are fixed or scaled against the parent.</p>
<p>This field is normally managed automatically when fields such as <fl>X</fl>, <fl>Y</fl>, <fl>Width</fl>, <fl>Height</fl>, <fl>XOffset</fl> and <fl>YOffset</fl> are changed.  If manual configuration is required, avoid conflicting fixed and scaled variants on the same axis.</p>
<types lookup="DMF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Display</name>
      <comment>Refers to the <class name="Display">Display</class> object that manages the surface's graphics.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>All surfaces belong to a <class name="Display">Display</class> object that manages drawing to the user's video display.  This field identifies the display that owns the surface.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Drag</name>
      <comment>Defines the <class name="Surface">Surface</class> that moves when this surface is dragged.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>Set this field to the <class name="Surface">Surface</class> that should move when the user starts a click-drag operation over the current surface. For example, a window title bar would set <code>Drag</code> to the window surface.  A surface may also set <code>Drag</code> to itself for icon-like or small draggable objects.</p>
<p>Set <code>Drag</code> to zero to disable drag handling.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DragStatus</name>
      <comment>Reports the current drag state when dragging is enabled.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type lookup="DRAG">DRAG</type>
      <description>
<p>Read this field to determine whether the surface is idle, anchored for dragging or actively being moved.</p>
<types lookup="DRAG"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Flags</name>
      <comment>Controls optional surface behaviour.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="RNF">RNF</type>
      <description>
<p>Use <code>Flags</code> to enable optional surface behaviours.  Preserve existing flags when updating this field, typically by combining the current value with the flags being added.</p>
<p>Read-only flags cannot be changed by writing this field.  Initialisation-only flags can be set before the surface is initialised, but are preserved once the surface is active.</p>
<types lookup="RNF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Height</name>
      <comment>Defines the height of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Use <code>Height</code> to read or change the surface height.  Alternatively, call <action>Resize</action> to change <fl>Width</fl> and <code>Height</code> together.</p>
<p>By default the value is a fixed coordinate unit.  With the <code>FD_SCALED</code> flag, the value is treated as a multiplier of the parent surface height.</p>
<p>Changing <code>Height</code> on a visible surface updates the displayed area immediately, including any child surfaces that need to be redrawn or resized.</p>
<p>Before initialisation, setting <code>Height</code> to zero or less clears the height dimension so that <fl>Y</fl> and <fl>YOffset</fl> can define the height dynamically.  After initialisation, values of zero or less are invalid.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>LeftLimit</name>
      <comment>Prevents a surface object from moving beyond a given point on the left-hand side.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>LeftLimit</code> to reserve a margin at the left-hand side of the parent container.  For example, a value of <code>3</code> prevents <action>Move</action> from placing the surface inside the left-most three coordinate units.</p>
<p>Movement limits apply only to <action>Move</action>.  Direct writes to coordinate fields bypass them.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MaxHeight</name>
      <comment>Prevents the height of a surface object from exceeding a certain value.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>MaxHeight</code> to limit the maximum height that can be applied through resizing.  <action>Resize</action> cannot increase the surface beyond this value.</p>
<p>Direct writes to <fl>Height</fl> bypass this limit.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MaxWidth</name>
      <comment>Prevents the width of a surface object from exceeding a certain value.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>MaxWidth</code> to limit the maximum width that can be applied through resizing.  <action>Resize</action> cannot increase the surface beyond this value.</p>
<p>Direct writes to <fl>Width</fl> bypass this limit.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MinHeight</name>
      <comment>Prevents the height of a surface object from shrinking beyond a certain value.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>MinHeight</code> to limit the minimum height that can be applied through resizing.  <action>Resize</action> cannot shrink the surface below this value.</p>
<p>Direct writes to <fl>Height</fl> bypass this limit.  Values less than <code>1</code> are clamped to <code>1</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MinWidth</name>
      <comment>Prevents the width of a surface object from shrinking beyond a certain value.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>MinWidth</code> to limit the minimum width that can be applied through resizing.  <action>Resize</action> cannot shrink the surface below this value.</p>
<p>Direct writes to <fl>Width</fl> bypass this limit.  Values less than <code>1</code> are clamped to <code>1</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Modal</name>
      <comment>Sets the surface as modal (prevents user interaction with other surfaces).</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>If set to <code>true</code>, the surface becomes the program's modal surface when shown.  This prevents interaction with other surfaces until the modal surface is hidden, destroyed or no longer modal.  Children of the modal surface remain interactive.</p>
<p>Clearing this field restores the previous modal surface if one was recorded.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Movement</name>
      <comment>Limits the movement of a surface object to vertical or horizontal shifts.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="MOVE">INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>Movement</code> to limit movement performed by <action>Move</action> to horizontal movement, vertical movement, both axes or neither axis.  By default, surfaces can move horizontally and vertically.</p>
<p>This field affects <action>Move</action> only.  Direct writes to coordinate fields bypass the movement restriction.</p>
<types lookup="MOVE"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Opacity</name>
      <comment>Defines the translucency applied when drawing a surface.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>
<code>Opacity</code> is expressed as a normalised multiplier.  The default value of <code>1.0</code> draws the surface as fully opaque.  Lower values make the surface more transparent.  Values outside the allowable range are clipped.</p>
<p>Non-opaque surfaces are drawn by rendering the surface content to its internal buffer and blending it with the background graphics.  This can be costly, and the pre-copy feature may give better results for some compositions.</p>
<p>Translucency can significantly increase CPU usage.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Parent</name>
      <comment>Identifies the parent <class name="Surface">Surface</class>.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>Child surfaces use this field to identify their parent.  Top-level surfaces have no parent.</p>
<p>If <code>Parent</code> is not set before initialisation, the surface class searches the ownership chain for the nearest <class name="Surface">Surface</class>. Set <code>Parent</code> to zero before initialisation to disable that automatic lookup.  An initialised child surface may be reparented, but a top-level surface cannot be converted into a child surface after initialisation.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>PopOver</name>
      <comment>Keeps a surface in front of another surface in the Z order.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>PopOver</code> before initialisation to the object ID of a sibling <class name="Surface">Surface</class> that this surface should stay in front of. For dialog windows, combine this field with <fl>Modal</fl> to keep the dialog in front and prevent interaction with other surfaces in the current program.</p>
<p>Set <code>PopOver</code> to zero before initialisation to use normal Z-order behaviour.</p>
<p>This field cannot be changed after initialisation.  The value must identify a <class name="Surface">Surface</class>; otherwise <code>ERR::InvalidObject</code> is returned.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Right</name>
      <comment>Returns the right-most coordinate of a surface object, <code>X + Width</code>.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>RightLimit</name>
      <comment>Prevents a surface object from moving beyond a given point on the right-hand side.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>RightLimit</code> to reserve a margin at the right-hand side of the parent container.  For example, a value of <code>8</code> prevents <action>Move</action> from placing the surface inside the right-most eight coordinate units.</p>
<p>Movement limits apply only to <action>Move</action>.  Direct writes to coordinate fields bypass them.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Root</name>
      <comment>Surface that is acting as a root for many surface children (useful when applying translucency)</comment>
      <access>-/-</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>TopLimit</name>
      <comment>Prevents a surface object from moving beyond a given point at the top of its container.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set <code>TopLimit</code> to reserve a margin at the top of the parent container.  For example, a value of <code>10</code> prevents <action>Move</action> from placing the surface inside the top-most ten coordinate units.</p>
<p>Movement limits apply only to <action>Move</action>.  Direct writes to coordinate fields bypass them.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>UserFocus</name>
      <comment>Refers to the surface object that has the current user focus.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Returns the object ID of the surface that has the primary user focus.  Returns zero if no surface has focus.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Visible</name>
      <comment>Indicates the visibility of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Read this field to determine whether the surface itself is marked visible.  A <code>true</code> value means the surface is shown; <code>false</code> means it is hidden.</p>
<p>Effective on-screen visibility also depends on the parent chain.  A visible child of a hidden parent is not displayed.</p>
<p>Set this field, or call <action>Hide</action> and <action>Show</action>, to change the surface visibility.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>VisibleHeight</name>
      <comment>The visible height of the surface area, relative to its parents.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Read <fl>VisibleX</fl>, <fl>VisibleY</fl>, <fl>VisibleWidth</fl> and <code>VisibleHeight</code> to determine the portion of the surface that is visible within the parent chain.</p>
<p>The visible area is calculated by clipping the surface area against its parent surfaces.  If a 100-unit-high surface is inside a 50-unit-high parent, at most 50 units can be visible, depending on the surface position.</p>
<p>If none of the surface area is visible, zero is returned.  The result is never negative.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>VisibleWidth</name>
      <comment>The visible width of the surface area, relative to its parents.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Read <fl>VisibleX</fl>, <fl>VisibleY</fl>, <code>VisibleWidth</code> and <fl>VisibleHeight</fl> to determine the portion of the surface that is visible within the parent chain.</p>
<p>The visible area is calculated by clipping the surface area against its parent surfaces.  If a 100-unit-wide surface is inside a 50-unit-wide parent, at most 50 units can be visible, depending on the surface position.</p>
<p>If none of the surface area is visible, zero is returned.  The result is never negative.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>VisibleX</name>
      <comment>The first visible X coordinate of the surface area, relative to its parents.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Read <code>VisibleX</code>, <fl>VisibleY</fl>, <fl>VisibleWidth</fl> and <fl>VisibleHeight</fl> to determine the portion of the surface that is visible within the parent chain.</p>
<p>
<code>VisibleX</code> is the first visible horizontal coordinate inside the surface's own coordinate space.  It is calculated by clipping the surface area against its parent surfaces.</p>
<p>If none of the surface area is visible, zero is returned.  The result is never negative.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>VisibleY</name>
      <comment>The first visible Y coordinate of the surface area, relative to its parents.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Read <fl>VisibleX</fl>, <code>VisibleY</code>, <fl>VisibleWidth</fl> and <fl>VisibleHeight</fl> to determine the portion of the surface that is visible within the parent chain.</p>
<p>
<code>VisibleY</code> is the first visible vertical coordinate inside the surface's own coordinate space.  It is calculated by clipping the surface area against its parent surfaces.</p>
<p>If none of the surface area is visible, zero is returned.  The result is never negative.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Width</name>
      <comment>Defines the width of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Use <code>Width</code> to read or change the surface width.  Alternatively, call <action>Resize</action> to change <code>Width</code> and <fl>Height</fl> together.</p>
<p>By default the value is a fixed coordinate unit.  With the <code>FD_SCALED</code> flag, the value is treated as a multiplier of the parent surface width.</p>
<p>Changing <code>Width</code> on a visible surface updates the displayed area immediately, including any child surfaces that need to be redrawn or resized.</p>
<p>Before initialisation, setting <code>Width</code> to zero or less clears the width dimension so that <fl>X</fl> and <fl>XOffset</fl> can define the width dynamically.  After initialisation, values of zero or less are invalid.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>WindowHandle</name>
      <comment>Refers to a surface object's window handle, if relevant.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>APTR</type>
      <description>
<p>This field exposes the host window handle for platforms that provide one.  It is currently relevant when creating a primary surface within an X11 window manager or Microsoft Windows.</p>
<p>Set <code>WindowHandle</code> before initialisation to attach the surface to an existing native window.  The field is immutable after initialisation.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>WindowType</name>
      <comment>Defines how a top-level surface is represented by a hosted desktop.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type lookup="SWIN">INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field affects hosted desktops such as Windows and X11.  It only applies to top-level surfaces that have no parent. Child surfaces ignore this field, and surfaces created inside the desktop area treat the desktop as their parent.</p>
<p>Custom surfaces remain responsible for their own window controls, such as title bars and resize borders.</p>
<types lookup="SWIN"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>X</name>
      <comment>Determines the horizontal position of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Use <code>X</code> to read or change the horizontal position of the surface relative to its parent.</p>
<p>By default the value is a fixed coordinate unit.  With the <code>FD_SCALED</code> flag, the value is treated as a multiplier of the parent surface width.</p>
<p>Changing <code>X</code> on a visible surface updates its position immediately.  If <fl>XOffset</fl> also defines the right-hand edge, the surface width is recalculated to preserve that offset.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>XOffset</name>
      <comment>Determines the horizontal offset of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>
<code>XOffset</code> defines a distance from the right-hand edge of the parent surface.</p>
<p>When <fl>X</fl> is set and <fl>Width</fl> is not set, <code>XOffset</code> makes the surface width dynamic.  The width extends from <fl>X</fl> to the parent width minus <code>XOffset</code>.</p>
<p>When <fl>Width</fl> is set, <code>XOffset</code> positions the surface from the parent right-hand edge: <code>X = ParentWidth - Width - XOffset</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Y</name>
      <comment>Determines the vertical position of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Use <code>Y</code> to read or change the vertical position of the surface relative to its parent.</p>
<p>By default the value is a fixed coordinate unit.  With the <code>FD_SCALED</code> flag, the value is treated as a multiplier of the parent surface height.</p>
<p>Changing <code>Y</code> on a visible surface updates its position immediately.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>YOffset</name>
      <comment>Determines the vertical offset of a surface object.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>
<code>YOffset</code> defines a distance from the bottom edge of the parent surface.</p>
<p>When <fl>Y</fl> is set and <fl>Height</fl> is not set, <code>YOffset</code> makes the surface height dynamic.  The height extends from <fl>Y</fl> to the parent height minus <code>YOffset</code>.</p>
<p>When <fl>Height</fl> is set, <code>YOffset</code> positions the surface from the parent bottom edge: <code>Y = ParentHeight - Height - YOffset</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="ALIGN" comment="Universal values for alignment of graphics and text">
      <const name="BOTTOM">Align to bottom</const>
      <const name="CENTER">Synonym for <code>HORIZONTAL | VERTICAL</code></const>
      <const name="HORIZONTAL">Align to horizontal center</const>
      <const name="LEFT">Align to left</const>
      <const name="MIDDLE">Synonym for <code>HORIZONTAL | VERTICAL</code></const>
      <const name="RIGHT">Align to right</const>
      <const name="TOP">Align to top</const>
      <const name="VERTICAL">Align to vertical center</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="BAF" comment="Instructions for basic graphics operations.">
      <const name="BLEND">Enable alpha blending to the destination if the source supports an alpha channel.</const>
      <const name="COPY">Special <function module="Display">CopyArea</function> option that avoids blending when the destination pixel is empty.</const>
      <const name="DITHER">Perform dithering if the colour formats differ between the source and destination.</const>
      <const name="FILL">For primitive operations such as <function module="Display">DrawRectangle</function>, this will fill the shape with a solid colour or texture.</const>
      <const name="LINEAR">Use linear interpolation to improve the quality of alpha blending.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="BDF" comment="CopySurface() flags">
      <const name="DITHER">Allow the use of dithering to improve image quality at a cost of speed.</const>
      <const name="REDRAW">Redraw the surface before performing the copy operation.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="CRF" comment="Flags for the SetCursor() function.">
      <const name="BUFFER">Use of the <code>BUFFER</code> option allows the cursor request to be buffered in the event that the cursor is locked at the time of calling the <function module="Display">SetCursor</function> function.  Use of this flag is highly recommended in most circumstances, but may not be used in conjunction with the <code>ANCHOR</code> option.</const>
      <const name="LMB">Release the cursor after the left mouse button is held and released.</const>
      <const name="MMB">Release the cursor after the middle mouse button is held and released.</const>
      <const name="NO_BUTTONS">Set the cursor only on the condition that the user is not holding down any buttons.  <code>ERR::NothingDone</code> is returned if the user has a button held down.</const>
      <const name="RESTRICT">Similar to the anchor option, but allows the pointer to move within the surface referred to by ObjectID.</const>
      <const name="RMB">Release the cursor after the right mouse button is held and released.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="CSRF" comment="Flags for CopySurface().">
      <const name="ALPHA">Enable alpha blending if the source is in 32-bit colour format with an alpha channel.</const>
      <const name="CLIP">Enable clipping of the source coordinates.</const>
      <const name="DEFAULT_FORMAT">Ignore the colour format defined in the source surface (if any) and generate a default format based on the <code>BitsPerPixel</code> value.</const>
      <const name="OFFSET">Adjust X and Y coordinates by the offset values defined in the <class name="Surface" field="XOffset">Surface.XOffset</class> and <class name="Surface" field="YOffset">Surface.YOffset</class> fields.</const>
      <const name="TRANSLUCENT">Perform a translucent copy operation, using the strength value specified in the <class name="Surface" field="Opacity">Surface.Opacity</class> field.</const>
      <const name="TRANSPARENT">Enable transparent copying, whereby colours matching the source's <code>Colour</code> field will be ignored.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="DMF">
      <const name="FIXED_CENTER_X">The CenterX field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_CENTER_Y">The CenterY field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_DEPTH">The Depth field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_HEIGHT">The Height field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_RADIUS_X">The RadiusX field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_RADIUS_Y">The RadiusY field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_WIDTH">The Width field is a fixed suze.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_X">The X field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_X_OFFSET">The XOffset field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Y">The Y field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Y_OFFSET">The YOffset field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Z">The Z field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_CENTER_X">The CenterX field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_CENTER_Y">The CenterY field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_DEPTH">The Depth field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_HEIGHT">The Height field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_RADIUS_X">The RadiusX field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_RADIUS_Y">The RadiusY field is a scaled size to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_WIDTH">The Width field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_X">The X field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_X_OFFSET">The XOffset field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Y">The Y field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Y_OFFSET">The YOffset field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Z">The Z field is a scaled coordinate to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="STATUS_CHANGE_H"/>
      <const name="STATUS_CHANGE_V"/>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="DRAG">
      <const name="ANCHOR">The surface is being dragged and the mouse pointer is anchored to the surface.</const>
      <const name="NONE">The surface is not being dragged.</const>
      <const name="NORMAL">The surface is being dragged.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="DT" comment="Flags for GetDisplayType().">
      <const name="GLES">The display is driven by OpenGLES.</const>
      <const name="NATIVE">The display is native (supported by internal drivers).</const>
      <const name="WINGDI">The display is driven by Microsoft Windows drivers.</const>
      <const name="X11">The display is driven by the X Window System (X11, X.Org, XFree86)</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="EXF" comment="Optional flags for the ExposeSurface() function.">
      <const name="ABSOLUTE">The supplied coordinates for exposure are absolute (relative to the display).</const>
      <const name="ABSOLUTE_COORDS">The supplied coordinates for exposure are absolute (relative to the display).</const>
      <const name="CHILDREN">If set, all child surfaces that intersect with exposed region will be included in the expose operation.</const>
      <const name="REDRAW_VOLATILE">Redraw every volatile object that intersects with the expose region, including internal volatile children.</const>
      <const name="REDRAW_VOLATILE_OVERLAP">Only redraw volatile objects that obscure the expose region from a position outside of the target surface and its children.  Useful if no redrawing has occurred in the surface, but the surface has moved to a new position and the parents need to be redrawn.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="HOST">
      <const name="STICK_TO_FRONT">The hosted display sticks to the front.</const>
      <const name="TASKBAR">The hosted display is given a taskbar button.</const>
      <const name="TRANSLUCENCE">Change the alpha channel level for the entire window.</const>
      <const name="TRANSPARENT">Defines an RGB colour that is to be used as transparent.</const>
      <const name="TRAY_ICON">All new displays are represented in the system tray when this option is active.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="JET" comment="JET constants are documented in GetInputEvent()">
      <const name="ABS_XY">The X, Y values are defined as absolute coordinates, relative to the top-left of the display.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_1">Left mouse button; XBox A button, PS square button.  Value is pressure sensitive, ranging between 0 - 1.0 (0 is released, 1.0 is fully depressed).</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_10">Non-specific button assignment.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_2">Right mouse button; XBox X button, PS cross button.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_3">Middle mouse button; XBox Y button, PS triangle.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_4">Alt. mouse button 1; XBox B button, PS circle.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_5">Alt. mouse button 2.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_6">Non-specific button assignment.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_7">Non-specific button assignment.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_8">Non-specific button assignment.</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_9">Non-specific button assignment.</const>
      <const name="CROSSED_IN">This message is sent by the input system when the mouse pointer enters an area for the first time.  The message value refers to the object ID of the container being monitored for movement.</const>
      <const name="CROSSED_OUT">This message is sent by the input system when the mouse pointer leaves an area.  The message value refers to the object ID of the container being monitored for movement.</const>
      <const name="DEVICE_TILT_XY">Controller tilted on the X/Y axis.  Value indicates angle, -ve = left, +ve = right</const>
      <const name="DEVICE_TILT_Z">Controller is rising or falling.  Value expressed as 'speed',</const>
      <const name="DISPLAY_EDGE">Recently supplied input occurred at the edge of the display.</const>
      <const name="PEN_TILT_XY">Pen tilt angle.  0 is pointing down directly with nib at bottom, 0.5 is 90 degrees, 1.0 is inversed (eraser at bottom)</const>
      <const name="PRESSURE">Amount of pressure applied, ranges from 0 (none) to 1.0 (normal) and possibly higher if user presses hard enough</const>
      <const name="WHEEL">Mouse wheel rotation - the value generally reflects the number of 'clicks' rotated on the wheel.</const>
      <const name="WHEEL_TILT">Some mouse wheels can be tilted to the left or right.  Ranges from -1.0 to +1.0</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="JTYPE" comment="JTYPE flags are used to categorise input types.">
      <const name="ANALOG">Analog movement (ranging from -1.0 to 1.0)</const>
      <const name="ANCHORED">Cursor has been anchored with LockCursor()</const>
      <const name="BUTTON">Input is a physical button or switch</const>
      <const name="CROSSING">Crossing events manage the entering and leaving of an area.</const>
      <const name="DBL_CLICK">Set by the input system if the <code>Type</code> is a button and the button has been clicked in quick succession so as to be classed as a double-click.</const>
      <const name="DIGITAL">D-Pad or digital joystick source (restricted to +/- 1)</const>
      <const name="DRAGGED">Set if sufficient movement occurred between the original click and its point of release (usually requires a 3 or more pixel difference).</const>
      <const name="DRAG_ITEM">This special flag is set by the input system if the pointer is click-dragging an object at the time of the event.</const>
      <const name="EXT_MOVEMENT">Extended or indirect movement information.  This covers all types of movement that are unconnected to coordinate positioning -  mouse wheel movement and pen tilt are two such examples.</const>
      <const name="MOVEMENT">X/Y coordinate movement only. Movement such as the wheel mouse spinning is not covered by this type as it does not influence the coordinate system.</const>
      <const name="REPEATED">Input is a repeated entry (i.e. user is holding down a button and a repetition timer is being triggered)</const>
      <const name="SECONDARY">Indicates to the receiver of this message that it is not the primary/original recipient</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="PTC" comment="Predefined cursor styles">
      <const name="CROSSHAIR">The cross hair is used for targeting specific pixel points (common in paint programs).</const>
      <const name="CUSTOM">Works in conjunction with the SetCustomCursor() function to represent a program defined bitmap.</const>
      <const name="DEFAULT">The default cursor (usually an arrow pointing to the upper left).</const>
      <const name="DRAGGABLE">Used to indicate that a surface or object can be dragged by the user.</const>
      <const name="END"/>
      <const name="HAND">The hand cursor is often used for indicating click-able content (hyper-links, icons etc).</const>
      <const name="HAND_LEFT">Similar to the standard hand cursor, but points to the left.</const>
      <const name="HAND_RIGHT">Similar to the standard hand cursor, but points to the right.</const>
      <const name="INVISIBLE">The cursor graphic is invisible (but will continue to operate as normal in all other respects).</const>
      <const name="MAGNIFIER">Represents a magnifying glass.</const>
      <const name="NO_CHANGE"/>
      <const name="PAINTBRUSH">The paintbrush cursor is typically employed by paint programs.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_BOTTOM">Sizing cursor - for resizing the bottom edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_BOTTOM_LEFT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the bottom left corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_BOTTOM_RIGHT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the bottom right corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_LEFT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the left edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_RIGHT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the right edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_TOP">Sizing cursor - for resizing the top edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_TOP_LEFT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the top left corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_TOP_RIGHT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the top right corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZING">Multi-directional sizing cursor - for resizing in any direction.</const>
      <const name="SLEEP">The sleep cursor is used to inform the user that the computer is busy.</const>
      <const name="SPLIT_HORIZONTAL">The horizontal split cursor is typically used for splitting rectangles in half, or dragging a horizontal split within a large rectangular space.</const>
      <const name="SPLIT_VERTICAL">The vertical split cursor is typically used for splitting rectangles in half, or dragging a vertical split within a large rectangular space.</const>
      <const name="STOP">The stop cursor is used to inform the user that an operation is not possible (e.g. drag and drop to an unsupported object area).</const>
      <const name="TEXT">The text cursor is popular for the precise positioning of text cursors.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="RNF" comment="Switches for the Surface class' Flags field.">
      <const name="AFTER_COPY">Read-only.  Indicates that after-copy mode has been enabled.</const>
      <const name="ASPECT_RATIO">When resizing, enforce the aspect ratio as defined by the diagonal from <class name="Surface" field="MinWidth">Surface.MinWidth</class>, <class name="Surface" field="MinHeight">Surface.MinHeight</class> to <class name="Surface" field="MaxWidth">Surface.MaxWidth</class>, <class name="Surface" field="MaxHeight">Surface.MaxHeight</class>.</const>
      <const name="AUTO_QUIT">The surface object will send a quit message to its supporting process when and if the Close method is called.  This flag is typically used when a surface object represents a core window for an application.</const>
      <const name="COMPOSITE">Do not copy background information into the surface buffer - composite on the fly instead</const>
      <const name="DISABLED">This flag is set if the Disable action has been called on a surface object.  Calling the Enable action will turn off the flag setting.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_BUFFER">Passes the <code>NEVER_SHRINK</code> option to the surface bitmap</const>
      <const name="FIXED_DEPTH">The target buffer always remains at the same depth</const>
      <const name="FULL_SCREEN">Allow the surface to open as a new screen display</const>
      <const name="GRAB_FOCUS">Helps application windows manage the user's focus within the window</const>
      <const name="HAS_FOCUS">Read-only.  If set, this flag indicates that the surface object currently has the focus.</const>
      <const name="HOST">Define host on initialisation to create a container that can host surfaces from other processes.</const>
      <const name="IGNORE_FOCUS">Focus is diverted directly to the parent</const>
      <const name="INIT_ONLY">Synonym for <code>HOST | TRANSPARENT | DISABLED | PRECOPY | VIDEO | FIXED_BUFFER | PERVASIVE_COPY | FIXED_DEPTH | FULL_SCREEN | IGNORE_FOCUS</code></const>
      <const name="NO_FOCUS">Prevents any kind of focussing on this object; no circumvention is possible</const>
      <const name="NO_HORIZONTAL">Turns off all horizontal movement (applies to the <code>Move()</code> action only).</const>
      <const name="NO_PRECOMPOSITE">Do not copy background information into the surface buffer - composite on the fly instead</const>
      <const name="NO_VERTICAL">Turns off all vertical movement (applies to the <code>Move()</code> action only).</const>
      <const name="PERVASIVE_COPY">This flag can be set in conjunction with after-copy mode.  It forces the after-copy support routine to copy graphics over the entire surface area, rather than avoiding the graphics of child surfaces.</const>
      <const name="POST_COMPOSITE">Do not copy background information into the surface buffer - composite on the fly instead</const>
      <const name="PRECOPY">Enables pre-copy mode, which means that all graphics behind the surface object are copied into the bitmap buffer prior to any redraw.  This mode can have a noticable impact on CPU time when drawing.</const>
      <const name="READ_ONLY">Synonym for <code>HAS_FOCUS | CURSOR | AFTER_COPY</code></const>
      <const name="STICKY">Prevents any response to the Move action.  It can be circumvented by writing to coordinate fields directly.</const>
      <const name="STICK_TO_BACK">Enable if the surface object must stick to the back of its container.</const>
      <const name="STICK_TO_FRONT">Enable if the surface object must stick to the front of its container.</const>
      <const name="TOTAL_REDRAW">Perform a total redraw of the entire surface when drawing - no partial draws</const>
      <const name="TRANSPARENT">Enables transparency, which means that the internal graphics routines will ignore this surface during redraws.  It is typically used when creating containers that will host other surfaces.</const>
      <const name="VIDEO">Set this flag if you would like the surface object's data to be managed in video memory only.  While this can give some speed advantages, be warned that video based surfaces are limited to write-only operations.</const>
      <const name="VISIBLE">If a surface object is visible to the user, the <code>VISIBLE</code> flag will be set.  If the flag is not set, the surface object is hidden.</const>
      <const name="VOLATILE">Synonym for <code>PRECOPY | AFTER_COPY | CURSOR</code></const>
      <const name="WRITE_ONLY">Set this flag if you would like the surface object's data to be managed in video memory only.  While this can give some speed advantages, be warned that video based surfaces are limited to write-only operations.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="RT">
      <const name="ROOT">Can be used by window surfaces to identify themselves as a root layer.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="SWIN" comment="Options for the Surface WindowType field.">
      <const name="HOST">Default to the standard hosted window mode with full titlebar, borders and taskbar representation.</const>
      <const name="ICON_TRAY">Create a borderless (custom) window with icon tray representation.</const>
      <const name="NONE">Create a borderless (custom) window with no UI representation.</const>
      <const name="TASKBAR">Create a borderless (custom) window with taskbar representation.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="WH" comment="Events for WindowHook()">
      <const name="CLOSE"/>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
    <struct name="BitmapSurface" typeName="BITMAPSURFACE">
      <field name="Data" type="APTR">Pointer to the bitmap graphics data.</field>
      <field name="Width" type="INT16">Pixel width of the bitmap.</field>
      <field name="Height" type="INT16">Pixel height of the bitmap.</field>
      <field name="LineWidth" type="INT">The distance between bitmap lines, measured in bytes.</field>
      <field name="BitsPerPixel" type="UINT8">The number of bits per pixel (8, 15, 16, 24, 32).</field>
      <field name="BytesPerPixel" type="UINT8">The number of bytes per pixel (1, 2, 3, 4).</field>
      <field name="Opacity" type="UINT8">Opacity level of the source if <code>CSRF::TRANSLUCENT</code> is used.</field>
      <field name="Version" type="UINT8">Version of this structure.</field>
      <field name="Colour" type="INT">Colour index to use if <code>CSRF::TRANSPARENT</code> is used.</field>
      <field name="Clip" type="struct ClipRectangle">A clipping rectangle will restrict drawing operations to this region if <code>CSRF::CLIP</code> is used.</field>
      <field name="XOffset" type="INT16">Offset all X coordinate references by the given value.</field>
      <field name="YOffset" type="INT16">Offset all Y coordinate references by the given value.</field>
      <field name="Format" type="struct ColourFormat">The colour format of this bitmap's pixels, or alternatively use <code>CSRF::DEFAULT_FORMAT</code>.</field>
    </struct>

    <struct name="ColourFormat" typeName="COLOURFORMAT">
      <field name="RedShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for red (15/16 bit formats only)</field>
      <field name="GreenShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for green</field>
      <field name="BlueShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for blue</field>
      <field name="AlphaShift" type="UINT8">Right shift value for alpha</field>
      <field name="RedMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for red (ranges from 0x00 to 0xff)</field>
      <field name="GreenMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for green</field>
      <field name="BlueMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for blue</field>
      <field name="AlphaMask" type="UINT8">Unshifted mask value for alpha</field>
      <field name="RedPos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for red</field>
      <field name="GreenPos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for green</field>
      <field name="BluePos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for blue</field>
      <field name="AlphaPos" type="UINT8">Left shift/positional value for alpha</field>
      <field name="BitsPerPixel" type="UINT8">Number of bits per pixel for this format.</field>
    </struct>

    <struct name="CursorInfo">
      <field name="Width" type="INT">Maximum cursor width for custom cursors</field>
      <field name="Height" type="INT">Maximum cursor height for custom cursors</field>
      <field name="Flags" type="INT">Currently unused</field>
      <field name="BitsPerPixel" type="INT16">Preferred bits-per-pixel setting for custom cursors</field>
    </struct>

    <struct name="DisplayInfo" typeName="DISPLAYINFO">
      <field name="Display" type="OBJECTID">Object ID related to the display</field>
      <field name="Flags" type="SCR" lookup="SCR">Display flags</field>
      <field name="Width" type="INT16">Pixel width of the display</field>
      <field name="Height" type="INT16">Pixel height of the display</field>
      <field name="BitsPerPixel" type="INT16">Bits per pixel</field>
      <field name="BytesPerPixel" type="INT16">Bytes per pixel</field>
      <field name="AccelFlags" type="ACF" lookup="ACF">Flags describing supported hardware features.</field>
      <field name="AmtColours" type="INT">Total number of supported colours.</field>
      <field name="PixelFormat" type="struct PixelFormat">The colour format to use for each pixel.</field>
      <field name="MinRefresh" type="FLOAT">Minimum refresh rate</field>
      <field name="MaxRefresh" type="FLOAT">Maximum refresh rate</field>
      <field name="RefreshRate" type="FLOAT">Recommended refresh rate</field>
      <field name="Index" type="INT">Display mode ID (internal)</field>
      <field name="HDensity" type="INT">Horizontal pixel density per inch.</field>
      <field name="VDensity" type="INT">Vertical pixel density per inch.</field>
    </struct>

    <struct name="InputEvent">
      <field name="Next" type="const struct InputEvent *">Next event in the chain</field>
      <field name="Value" type="DOUBLE">The value associated with the Type</field>
      <field name="Timestamp" type="INT64">PreciseTime() of the recorded input</field>
      <field name="RecipientID" type="OBJECTID">Surface that the input message is being conveyed to</field>
      <field name="OverID" type="OBJECTID">Surface that is directly under the mouse pointer at the time of the event</field>
      <field name="AbsX" type="DOUBLE">Absolute horizontal position of mouse cursor (relative to the top left of the display)</field>
      <field name="AbsY" type="DOUBLE">Absolute vertical position of mouse cursor (relative to the top left of the display)</field>
      <field name="X" type="DOUBLE">Horizontal position relative to the surface that the pointer is over - unless a mouse button is held or pointer is anchored - then the coordinates are relative to the click-held surface</field>
      <field name="Y" type="DOUBLE">Vertical position relative to the surface that the pointer is over - unless a mouse button is held or pointer is anchored - then the coordinates are relative to the click-held surface</field>
      <field name="DeviceID" type="OBJECTID">The hardware device that this event originated from</field>
      <field name="Type" type="JET" lookup="JET">JET constant that describes the event</field>
      <field name="Flags" type="JTYPE" lookup="JTYPE">Broad descriptors for the given <code>Type</code> (see <code>JTYPE</code> flags).  Automatically defined when delivered to the pointer object</field>
      <field name="Mask" type="JTYPE" lookup="JTYPE">Mask to use for checking against subscribers</field>
    </struct>

    <struct name="SurfaceInfo" typeName="SURFACEINFO">
      <field name="Data" type="APTR">Bitmap data memory ID</field>
      <field name="ParentID" type="OBJECTID">Object that contains the surface area</field>
      <field name="BitmapID" type="OBJECTID">Surface bitmap buffer</field>
      <field name="DisplayID" type="OBJECTID">Refers to the display if this object is at root level</field>
      <field name="Flags" type="RNF" lookup="RNF">Surface flags</field>
      <field name="X" type="INT">Horizontal coordinate</field>
      <field name="Y" type="INT">Vertical coordinate</field>
      <field name="Width" type="INT">Width of the surface area</field>
      <field name="Height" type="INT">Height of the surface area</field>
      <field name="AbsX" type="INT">Absolute X coordinate</field>
      <field name="AbsY" type="INT">Absolute Y coordinate</field>
      <field name="Level" type="INT16">Branch level within the tree</field>
      <field name="BitsPerPixel" type="INT8">Bits per pixel of the bitmap</field>
      <field name="BytesPerPixel" type="INT8">Bytes per pixel of the bitmap</field>
      <field name="LineWidth" type="INT">Line width of the bitmap, in bytes</field>
    </struct>

  </structs>
</book>
